<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons viz. 1. A commission for an assise, granted to the saints, 2. A close hypocrite discovered, 3. The lawfulnesse of doing good out of hope of reward / by Daniel Cawdrey ...</title>
            <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7914</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12331840</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12331840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59698</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59698)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 934:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons viz. 1. A commission for an assise, granted to the saints, 2. A close hypocrite discovered, 3. The lawfulnesse of doing good out of hope of reward / by Daniel Cawdrey ...</title>
                  <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.Y. for Ph. Nevill, and are to be sold by Peter Whaley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Each of the three sermons has a separate t.p.: "A commission for an assise, or, A remedie against lawing ..."; "Epichairekakia, or, A close hypocrite discovered"; "Vindicæ spei, shewing the lawfulnesse of doing good out of hope of reward".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59698:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59698:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS: <hi>viz:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A Commiſsion for an Aſsiſe, granted to the Saints.</item>
                  <item>2. A cloſe Hypocrite diſcovered.</item>
                  <item>3. The Lawfulneſſe of doing Good out of Hope of Reward.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Daniel Cawdrey,</hi> Rector of Great Billing in Northampton-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PHIL. 2.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vaine glory, but in lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind let each esteeme other better then themſelves.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.Y.</hi> for <hi>Ph. Nevill,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Peter Whaley</hi> at his ſhop in Northampton. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:2"/>
                  <p>A COMMISSION FOR AN ASSISE, Granted to the SAINTS: OR, A Remedie againſt Lawing.</p>
                  <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon at the Aſſiſes held at Northampton. <hi>Iuly</hi> 9. 1640.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>D.C.</hi> Rector of Great Billing in Northampton ſhire.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>REVEL. 20.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And I ſaw ſeats, and they ſate upon them, and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given unto them.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 149. ult.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Such honour have all his Saints.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.Y.</hi> for <hi>Phil. Nevill,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gun in Ivie-lane. 1641.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:3"/>
                  <head>To the Right VVorſhipfull Sir CHRISTOPHER YELVERTON, Knight (late) High Sheriffe of the Countie of Northampton, all health and happineſſe.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the manner of Midwives, ſo ſoon as the childe is borne and dreſſed, to preſent it firſt to the owne parents, and then to the view of others. This follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon, as it was first conceived by your motion and requeſt (which is to me a virtuall command) ſo it is but fit and reaſon, that it ſhould firſt be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred back unto you, that the ſame partie that helped to give it life and bringing forth, might alſo give it protection and bringing up. The ſucceſſe and operation that it had (as I am made beleeve) in the hearts of them who heard it firſt ſpeake, made me the more willing to expoſe it to the eyes of others, to ſee if it might ſomewhat prevaile to ſtifle, and (as <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> the ſerpents in his cradle) to ſtrangle the lawleſſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Lawing age. I have long and often lamented to ſee how all the world almoſt is turn'd into one common Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, either to ſue, or cenſure others. The great reſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ancient times were wont to be for counſell to the houſes of the Prophets: But now the Innes of Court, and Courts of Justice are more peſtered with Clients, than the very houſes of God. Hence it is, that for the moſt part, that Profeſſion of the Law thrives beſt of any; and thoſe that, perhaps ſome of them, envy an <hi>100.</hi> L. <hi>per annum</hi> to a painfull Levite, with a great deale more eaſe, themſelves get <hi>500.</hi> L. and think it
<pb facs="tcp:59698:4"/>nothing. The peeviſh perverſeneſſe of men, is much guiltie of this thrift. For if men had either ſo much grace, or wit, to doe no wrong; or if they doe, or ſuffer wrong, to be willing to referre it to their wiſe and honeſt brethren, they might have both more peace in their minds, and alſo more mony in their purſes. And I cannot but wonder at the frowardneſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of men, that rather chuſe to referre it to twelve men, and they ſtrangers, by force and courſe of the Law; than to two men their neighbours and friends, by the perſwaſion of the Goſpel. In which proceedings, there is this diſadvantage at leaſt (beſides many more) that whereas they might have choſen Arbitrators, wiſe and honeſt, their differences fall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes into the hands of many, whereof ſome are wiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, but not honeſt; others are honeſt, but no wiſer than they ſhould be: In which caſes, a good cauſe, many times, falls to the ground. To prevent which miſchiefe, was, at leaſt, one maine intention of this Sermon. Knowing the weakneſſe of it to walke alone, I have ſent forth with it, two of its elder bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, (two other Sermons, preached on other occaſions) to wait upon it, (and with it upon you, Sir) as poore folkes uſe to doe, who ſet the elder to tend upon the younger. Such is your noble Candor (as I well know) that you will both protect theſe now made your own, and alſo lovingly accept, what is ſo duly, ſo reſpectfully tendered; not only as a private pledge, but alſo as a publike acknowledgement to the world, of my many great ingagements for your many undeſerved, undeſired favours. And I ſhall never ceaſe (till I ceaſe to be my ſelfe) to ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Almighty, for Grace, Mercy and Peace upon your worthy ſelfe, your vertuous Lady, and hopefull off-ſpring: taking it for none of the leaſt favours, that I may profeſſe my ſelfe to bee</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in all due reſpects, and ſervice in the Lord. DANIEL CAWDREY.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>illing Magna. <date>Novemb. <hi>20. 1640.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59698:4"/>
                  <head>A COMMISSION FOR AN ASSISE, Granted to the SAINTS.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. COR. 6.2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Doe you not know, that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> having,<note place="margin">Coherence.</note> in the former Chapter, taxed theſe <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for their great <hi>Negligence,</hi> in not-judging that inceſtuous perſon, in a caſe Eccleſiaſticall; Now, in this Chapter, he blames them, for their over-much <hi>Diligence,</hi> in going to Judgement, in a matter civill and politicall. He doth not inveigh againſt, much leſſe utterly aboliſh (as ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> dreame) the uſe of ſecular Jugdements, which we call going to Law: but onely reprehends the <hi>Abuſes,</hi> which he obſerved amongſt them, in the uſe of that,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59698:5"/>which in it ſelfe (and ſome caſes excepted) might be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>Wee know,</hi> (to uſe our Apoſtles owne words, of another <hi>Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.8.</note> the Law of God) <hi>the Law is good, if a man uſe it lawfully.</hi> Which (at once to confute them, and paſſe along) wee may eaſily make good, from this very place. For the ſame <hi>Apostle</hi> that denies them the uſe of Law, in regard of ſome circumſtances, allowes it, in regard of others. Hee denyes it in regard of <hi>Infidels,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sanctis diſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatoribus. Beza in locum.</note> allowes it in regard of the <hi>Saints,</hi> that is, of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> as the firſt verſe implyes. But the beſt thing may be abuſed; and ſo is, too oft, the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelfe. Yet if the abuſe may cry downe the uſe of a thing, we muſt pull downe the <hi>Sunne</hi> out of the Firmament. It is true, <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Warre,</hi> are much alike: <hi>Warre</hi> is but a more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like kind of <hi>Lawing;</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> is but a more private kind of <hi>Warring;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ne hoc quidem remedio egerent. Id. in ver. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> and both of them <hi>Remedies</hi> of the laſt <hi>Refuge.</hi> Yea this we will ſay more, (if that may pleaſe and ſatisfie our ſecular <hi>Antinomians</hi>) that if men were but ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,</hi> as they ſhould be, there would be either none, or little uſe, either of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> or <hi>Lawyers.</hi> If men had but ſo much <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> to doe no <hi>wrong,</hi> or ſo much <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Charitie,</hi> if they doe wrong, to doe <hi>right:</hi> as on the one ſide, our <hi>Armour</hi> might ruſt in our houſes; ſo on the other, the <hi>Courts</hi> of Juſtice might have more <hi>Cobwebs</hi> than <hi>Cauſes,</hi> more <hi>Spiders</hi> than <hi>Clients.</hi> But this may not be expected (feare it not, O you champions of Warre, or Advocates of either Law) whiles two bitter <hi>rootes</hi> grow in the hearts of men, <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Selfe-love.</hi> The one, whereby they will doe no <hi>right;</hi> the other, whereby they will take no <hi>wrong.</hi> The beſt way therefore, that I know, is to conſider, ſeriouſly, what are the faults that uſually men bring, or rather bring men to thoſe <hi>Tribunals,</hi> and, as much as we can, to labour every one to redreſſe them. Our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath noted ſome, and the chiefeſt, to our hands.</p>
                  <p>Many were their errours in that proceeding: ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the <hi>Plaintiffe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Errors in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law, in</note> ſome the <hi>Defendant,</hi> ſome the <hi>Spectators.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. The Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, that</note> the <hi>Plaintiffe;</hi> and what he wants in waight, he hath in number; and they are five.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59698:5"/> 1.<note place="margin">1. With a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Firſt, in regard of his <hi>Adverſary;</hi> who is noted, not onely generally to be a <hi>Corinthian,</hi> but to be a <hi>Chriſtian: Dare any of you,</hi> you Chriſtian <hi>Corinthians:</hi> and, <hi>A brother goeth to Law with a brother,</hi> verſ. 6. Infidell to goe to Law with Infidell, were not ſtrange. Infidell with Chriſtian was too common. But Chriſtian with Chriſtian, brother with brother, ſeemes both unnaturall, and (as thoſe times were) unchriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In regard of the <hi>Judge,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Before Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</note> choſen to decide and umpire their controverſies: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, under the unjuſt, verſe the firſt: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, verſ. 6. under the Infidels, or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, and not under the Saints. If brother will goe to Law with brother, let them make choice of Chriſtian Judges. For Infidels to be judged by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not unfit; But for Chriſtians, to refuſe Chriſtians, and to chuſe to be judged by Infidels, was foulely<note n="*" place="margin">Quod eligerent voluntariè Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Aquin. in locum.</note> ſcandalous. What will the heathens ſay, when <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are together by the eares, and <hi>Infidels</hi> live in unitie?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In regard of the <hi>Matter:</hi> ſome trifles, of no moment;<note place="margin">3. For Trifles.</note> as in the later end of this ſecond verſe, <hi>Are you unworthy to judge the least matters?</hi> Should men, that I ſay not Chriſtians, fight, as two Cocks, for a graine of barly? for a Gooſe in the graſſe? or a Pigge in the corne? It is a fault too common, every pettie difference peſters theſe Tribunals. <hi>Gallio</hi> ſhould doe well to drive them from the Judgement ſeate, with that word, <hi>I will be no Judge of ſuch matters.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 18.15, 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. In regard of the <hi>Manner:</hi> with a great deale of <hi>Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and impotent Anger: verſe 7.<note place="margin">4. With Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</note> 
                     <hi>Why doe you not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take wrong? why doe you not rather ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded?</hi> where the Apoſtle prevents a ſecret ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: They might plead; We doe not thus proceed without a cauſe; we have been wronged, perhaps very much, and may we not ſeeke the benefit of the Law, to right our ſelves? No, ſayes the holy Apoſtle; ſomething ſhould bee hazzarded, yea loſt, for peace ſake. <hi>Chriſt</hi> your maſter taught you this leſſon, <hi>If any man will take away thy cloake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>let him have thy coate alſo:</hi> Peace is a Jewell, if we knew the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59698:6"/> worth of it, worth our buying, at a dearer rate than moſt men will give for it: And beſides, S. <hi>James</hi> hath told us the diſpoſition of all truely godly hearts, <hi>The Wiſedome which is from above,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 3.17.</note> 
                     <hi>is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy, &amp;c.</hi> Now verily, there is utterly a fault among you, that you want that Chriſtian Patience, to ſuffer ſome wrong, rather than goe to Law.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. Too preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate.</note> In regard of the <hi>Order:</hi> Law ſhould be your laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, after tryall of all other <hi>Meanes</hi> in vaine. Amongſt the reſt, <hi>Reference</hi> unto your brethren, ſhould be uſed: If they cannot end it, the Law is open, implead one another. And this was a principall fault amongſt them, that ſo ſoone as any difference aroſe, they ranne or ſent preſently for a <hi>Writt</hi> to the heatheniſh Courts, and refuſed to referre it to the <hi>Saints,</hi> as the firſt verſe intimates.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. The Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant,</note> there are other faults that concerne the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant;</hi> and what he wants in number, he hath in waight.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. In doing the wrong.</note> That he did the <hi>wrong,</hi> and ſo was the occaſion, or cauſe of all, or moſt of thoſe errours in the Plaintiffe, verſe 8. <hi>Nay you doe wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. In defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wrong done.</note> That he <hi>Defended</hi> the wrong done, by denyall of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, to doe his brother right; whereupon he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon thoſe ſcandalous and ſinfull courſes. Nay it may ſeeme, that he that did the wrong, did not onely defend it, but alſo turned <hi>Plaintiffe,</hi> (as we call him that begins a ſuit) and beganne to ſue him firſt, as the manner of ſome great ones is; either to vexe him, or make him unable to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the former wrong, or to make themſelves ſeeme inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; For, attend the Apoſtles words: <hi>Why doe you not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take wrong?</hi> which concernes the <hi>Plaintiffe,</hi> without all queſtion: yea (but addes the Apoſtle) <hi>you doe wrong, and defraud;</hi> which, in all congruitie, muſt concerne the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant:</hi> As if he were both <hi>Plaintiffe</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant</hi> (a ſtrange myſterie) that is, <hi>Plaintiffe</hi> in the ſuite, but <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> of the wrong done, by firſt complaining. However, there was certainly a fault amongſt them, in one, or other, or both; yea, both, no doubt, are too often to blame. <hi>There
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59698:6"/>is utterly a fault, that you goe to Law one with another,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, verſ. 7. that there are any cauſes between you, which need the <hi>Judgement</hi> and deciſion of the Law. It is hardly poſſible to goe to Law, but that the one partie, at leaſt, is faultie.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Spectators,</hi> or by-ſtanders,<note place="margin">3. The Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; their</note> were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innocent. Two faults there are to be found in them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their ſimplicitie or <hi>Ignorance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Ignorance.</note> that they were not able to comprimiſe their brethrens differences, before they went ſo farre, verſe 5. <hi>I ſpeake it to your ſhame, is it ſo, that there is not a wiſe man amongst you? no, not one, that is able to judge between his brethren? but a brother goeth to law with a brother?</hi> &amp;c. Now verily there is utterly a fault amongſt you, even you, that ſtand and looke on theſe unkind bickerings, and want skill to quiet them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their ſloath or <hi>Negligence,</hi> that they were ſo lazie,<note place="margin">2. Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> that they would ſuffer their brethren to goe to Law, and that under Infidels, rather than diſ-eaſe themſelves a little, to compoſe them, being deſigned by God himſelfe to be <hi>Judges</hi> of the world. Theſe, I take it, are the principall faults the Apoſtle finds with this proceeding of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians;</hi> which being amended, <hi>Law</hi> is, no doubt, lawfull, ſay <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> what they can to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>And now we come more neerer to the words. My Text hath reference to all the three; but primarily to the <hi>Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe;</hi> and it is brought in as an argument, to diſſwade his courſe, and to diſprove his choice. The ſumme ſeemes to be thus much: O <hi>Corinthians,</hi> O Chriſtians,<note place="margin">The Summe of the words.</note> you are much to blame, that chuſe ſuch incompetent <hi>Judges,</hi> of your diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, as <hi>Infidels</hi> are; <hi>Dare any of you, having a matter againſt another, be judged under the Infidels, and not under the Saints?</hi> The expoſtulation is very quick and ſharpe; If you will needs referre your cauſe to <hi>Judgement,</hi> in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Saints,</hi> were fitter <hi>Judges</hi> than they. Why ſo? why, <hi>Doe you not know, that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If you chuſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> and refuſe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> you too much <hi>honour</hi> the one, and <hi>diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59698:7"/> the other. You too much <hi>honour</hi> Infidels in ſuffering, much more in voluntarily <hi>offering</hi> your ſelves to be <hi>judged</hi> by them,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. verſ. 7. <hi>mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio eſt:</hi> a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraging.</note> whom you ſhall one day <hi>judge.</hi> You diſhonour and diſparage <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> double: Firſt, your ſelves, in that you make your ſelves inferiour to thoſe that ſhall, one day, be <hi>judged</hi> by you: As for example, Were it a beſeeming thing, that the Honourable <hi>Judges</hi> of Aſſiſe, ſhould referre themſelves,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chryſ. in locum.</note> in any matter of difference, to be judged by the Priſoners in the Gaole, whom they ſhall by and by judge? <hi>Doe you not know, that the Saints, even you ſhall judge the world? If then the world ſhall be judged by you,</hi> (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle argues in the latter part of this verſe) is it fit that you ſhould be judged by the world? Secondly, you <hi>diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> your fellow <hi>Saints,</hi> to undervalue them ſo much, as to thinke <hi>Infidels</hi> worthy of that honour of <hi>Judicature,</hi> rather than them, who ſhall one day judge the world: As if ſome perſons that have buſineſſe at this <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> ſhould refuſe the honourable <hi>Bench,</hi> and referre themſelves to the Priſoners, who muſt be judged by the <hi>Bench.</hi> The argument lyes thus, <hi>à majore ad minus:</hi> If the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall judge the <hi>world,</hi> then, much more, leſſer differences of their brethren, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things of this life: that's the latter part of this verſe. But certainly the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall judge the world, that's the former part of this verſe, (for take off the Rhetoricall Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, and it is a ſtrong Affirmation) Therefore the Saints are the fitteſt <hi>Judges</hi> of Chriſtians leſſer differences. You have the Coherence and ſcope of the words; Now take the Summe of them, conſidered abſolutely in themſelves. They are (if I may be bold to borrow your owne termes) <hi>A Commiſsion for an Aſsiſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Commiſſion of Saints: In it</note> 
                     <hi>granted to the Saints:</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in them two generall parts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Dignitie</hi> it ſelfe; The Saints ſhall judge the world; and therein, we may conſider three things:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> deſigned, by the name of <hi>Saints.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Matter</hi> of the Commiſſion, that is, to <hi>judge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>Latitude,</hi> or extent of that Commiſſion, the <hi>world. The Saints ſhall judge the world.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59698:7"/> 2. The <hi>Certaintie</hi> thereof: <hi>Doe you not know this?</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, You doe know it, you muſt know it.</p>
                  <p>We begin firſt, with the <hi>Dignitie,</hi> and therein</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. The Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; where</note> The <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> deputed, The <hi>Saints:</hi> wherein we have two things to conſider, Their <hi>Qualitie,</hi> Saints;<note place="margin">1. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners; both</note> Their <hi>Equalitie,</hi> all the Saints: the one in the ſenſe and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the word, the other in the Indefiniteneſſe and Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of the Number: we touch upon both.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Qualitie,</hi> the Saints: The word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; Holy For 3. reaſons.</note> ſignifies <hi>Holy,</hi> which in the largeſt acception of it, is equivalent to that of <hi>Juſt,</hi> or <hi>Righteous,</hi> as might appeare from other places; and muſt be ſo taken here, as the oppoſition in the former verſe doth evidently manifeſt; For it is not there oppoſed to profane, but to the <hi>unjuſt,</hi> that is to <hi>Infidels</hi> or unbeleevers, that were generally unjuſt or unrighteous, as having no true Chriſtian <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> in them: And as, Righteouſneſſe in Scripture and other authors,<note place="margin">Juſtitia in ſeſe virtutes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net omnes.</note> containes in it, not onely that particular vertue of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but all vertues whatſoever; in a generall notion: So <hi>Unrighteouſneſſe</hi> doth not onely ſignifie that particular vice of <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> (from which many heathen Judges were free) but even the want of all the vertues, or the moſt of them. In the 9. and 10. verſes of this Chapter, laid together, the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines what he meanes by the unjuſt, or unrighteous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Know you not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherite the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God?</hi> The unrighteous? who are they? marke the next verſe: <hi>Neither Whoremongers, nor Idolaters, &amp;c.</hi> Now then, if <hi>unjuſt</hi> ſignifie all kind of unrighteouſneſſe; the <hi>Saints,</hi> or Holy, being thereunto oppoſed, muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe include all <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Summe</hi> is, <hi>All Gods Commiſsioners for the heavenly Judicature, muſt be Saints, holy, harmeleſſe, innocent, righteous:</hi> that's the point. Every man is not fit to be made a <hi>Judge</hi> on earth; much leſſe in heaven: There are three things, we know, that make a compleate <hi>Judge</hi> on earth, <hi>Authoritie, Prudence, Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Selfe-Innocence:</hi> The firſt is founded in his <hi>Commiſion;</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59698:8"/> and is without himſelfe: The other two are within himſelfe, inherent in his perſon: And if the queſtion be, Which of the two is moſt requiſite for a <hi>Judge?</hi> I ſhould venture to ſay the latter, <hi>Holineſſe</hi> or Innocence, for theſe reaſons:</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. To be like God.</note> 
                     <hi>Justice</hi> or <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> makes God himſelfe a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and Compleate <hi>Judge</hi> of the world: ſo the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture oft reſolves it: <hi>Shall not the Judge of heaven and earth doe right?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> ſayes <hi>Abraham. What ſhall we ſay then? Is there unrighteouſneſſe with God?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 3.5.</note> 
                     <hi>God forbid: for how ſhall God then judge the world?</hi> ſayes our Apoſtle: As if he ſhould ſay, God himſelfe (with reverence bee it ſpoken) were not a Competent <hi>Judge,</hi> if that he were not perfectly <hi>righteous: The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes:</hi> Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe in God, are of equall latitude and extent: Now as God is King of Kings, ſo he is Judge of Judges, and all his Judges muſt be like himſelfe;<note place="margin">Rev. 15.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Holy</hi> as he is Holy; and therefore called <hi>King of Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. To avoid Recriminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to avoid reproach, and <hi>Recrimination:</hi> If a Judge want <hi>Innocence</hi> or <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> he is expoſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and ſhall be upbraided with his owne errours. <hi>Thou that teacheſt another,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.21.</note> 
                     <hi>teachest thou not thy ſelfe?</hi> was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to one of our coate. Wee may enlarge it: Thou that <hi>judgest</hi> another, <hi>judgeſt</hi> thou not thy ſelfe? Thou that condemneſt a man for ſtealing, doeſt thou ſteale? Thou that abhorreſt Symonie, doeſt thou commit Briberie? &amp;c. As that Pyrate under cenſure, retorted upon the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, What I do by ſea, thou doeſt that and more by land: and, many times,<note place="margin">Ibid. verſ. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Great</hi> theeves condemne little ones: <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt; for thou that judgeſt another, condemneſt thy ſelfe, for thou that judgeſt doeſt the ſame things,</hi> or ſome thing as bad.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. To prevent Partialitie.</note> to prevent <hi>Partialitie:</hi> For ſelfe-guiltineſſe commonly makes men partiall, in judging others: Their Conſcience holds both tongue and hand, and tells them, they doe but beat themſelves, whiles they puniſh others:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59698:8"/> We may ſee it in <hi>Judah:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 38.</note> when his daughter in law <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> was accuſed for her Incontinencie, how raſhly hee cenſures, <hi>Bring her forth, and let her be burned;</hi> But when he heard, <hi>By the man whoſe theſe are, am I with child;</hi> the caſe is altered, <hi>Shee is more righteous than I;</hi> no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talke of burning now; unleſſe himſelfe will be burned with her: Now on earth, it is too evident, that <hi>Selfe-iniquitie</hi> is the mother of <hi>Partialitie:</hi> Therefore <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> giving charge to his Judges, to doe juſtly, enforces it from the example of God, whoſe <hi>Judges</hi> they are: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with the Lord, there is no iniquitie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chro. 19.6.</note> 
                     <hi>nor respect of perſons, nor taking of gifts:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If there be <hi>Iniquitie</hi> in the heart, there will be reſpect of perſons, and taking of gifts, to pervert Juſtice: Requiſite therefore it is, that they who ſhall be counted worthy, to be <hi>Judges</hi> in heaven, ſhould be <hi>Saints,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> privative and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>terra:</hi> men, that are like pure Gold, purified ſeven times in the fire, purged from the <hi>droſſe</hi> of earthly corruptions; or like pure wine defecated and wracked from the <hi>Lees</hi> and dregs of carnall affections:
<note place="margin">Incorruptus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adutabilis, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra improbos immiſericors, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorabilis, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtate aequita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, veritatiſque terribilis. Au. Gell. li. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> Such as <hi>Chryſippus</hi> would have all earthly Judges: <hi>Incorrupt, unflatterable, unmercifull and inexorable toward wicked men, terrible in the Majeſtie of equitie and truth.</hi> Men free from paſſion and compaſſion; that will know neither father nor mother, friend nor bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as was ſaid of <hi>Levi</hi> in a like caſe: For ſuppoſe a <hi>Judge</hi> ſhould meete, at the barre, his child, or brother, &amp;c. and they ſhould intreat, by thoſe neere relations, O my <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> O my <hi>Brother,</hi> &amp;c. What heart, not throughly harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, could reſiſt ſuch <hi>melting</hi> compellations? perhaps it will be thus, at the great day of <hi>Judgement;</hi> we have a type of it in the Goſpell; where our Saviour brings in, (whether by way of Parable, or true Hiſtorie) the rich man beholding <hi>Abraham</hi> afarre off, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his boſome; Hee dare not ſpeake to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who was perhaps a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and was by him before neglected; but to <hi>Abraham</hi> he addreſſes himſelfe, with that oylie name of <hi>Father; Father Abraham have mercy upon your ſonne:</hi> But <hi>Abraham</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59698:9"/>was now above relations, above compaſsions, and fooliſh pittie: <hi>Sonne remember, &amp;c.</hi> So at that great Day there will be crying, O my father, O my ſonne, O my husband, O my brother! But there muſt be <hi>judgement without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> They, the <hi>Judges</hi> there, muſt be as inſenſible, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was; and if not pronounce, yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and applaud that dreadfull ſentence upon their deareſt acquaintance and friends, <hi>Goe ye curſed into everlaſting fire, &amp;c.</hi> What manner of men then ought they to be, that muſt be Judges of the world,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11.</note> in <hi>all Holineſſes and Godlineſſes</hi> (ſo the Apoſtles words are) that is in the perfection of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> and Godlineſſe;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>perfecting Holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> as our Apoſtle ſpeakes. To conclude this firſt point; However on earth, favour or affection, briberie or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may ſometime make a <hi>Judge;</hi> as that <hi>Romane</hi> could ſay, to his little credite,<note place="margin">Act. 22.28.</note> 
                     <hi>With a great ſumme of mony, obtained I this office:</hi> yet in heaven none but <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall judge the world: and that's the firſt. The ſecond is</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Equalitie; Sancti,</hi> in the plurall, and indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, the <hi>Saints:</hi> and I feare not to ſay, in the words of Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 149.</note> 
                     <hi>Such honour have all his Saints:</hi> They are fellow-Commiſſioners; If I miſtake not, all our Judges are ſo; and ſo are all our <hi>Juſtices</hi> at the Quarter <hi>Seſſions;</hi> one Commiſſion includes them all: There are indeed diſtinct <hi>altitudes,</hi> in reſpect of their perſonall titles, and degrees, but no different <hi>latitudes,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>Commiſsion;</hi> therein they are all equall. Heaven obſerves the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion: <hi>One ſtarre differs from another in glory,</hi> not in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The leaſt is as true a ſtarre, as thoſe of the greateſt magnitude: One <hi>Saint</hi> differs from another, perhaps, in perſonall <hi>glory</hi> in heaven, as in perſonall <hi>grace</hi> on earth; but the meaneſt, the loweſt, is as truely a Saint, as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and as truly a <hi>Commiſsioner</hi> and Judge of the world. There may and muſt be difference of order and prioritie, to avoid confuſion, but no diſparitie of dignitie in this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Judicature.<note place="margin">Math. 19.28.</note> Our Saviour tels his diſciples ſo: <hi>You ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Jſrael.</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59698:9"/>They have all thrones, all ſit, all judge; <hi>Matthias</hi> the laſt, as well as <hi>Peter</hi> the firſt. What? onely the twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? ſhall none ſit upon <hi>thrones</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> but they? what ſhall then become of <hi>Paul,</hi> and other Saints? He that made the queſtion, can beſt reſolve it, S. <hi>Auguſtine. Wee ought not to thinke</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that onely thoſe twelve men ſhall judge with Christ. For by that number,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Civit. Dei, lib. <hi>20.6.5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>is ſignified the whole multitude of Judges. Otherwiſe the Apoſtle</hi> Paul, <hi>who laboured more than all of them, ſhall want a roome to ſit on; who yet demonſtrates, that himſelfe with other Saints, doe belong to that number, when he ſaith, Doe you not know that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi> and againe in the next verſe, <hi>Know you not that we ſhall judge Angels?</hi> The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Schoolmen (falſly ſo called) ſome of them are here not Catholike enough;
<note place="margin">Aquin. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> They reſtraine this <hi>Dignitie</hi> onely to the Apoſtles, and ſuch as have followed them; by profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vowed povertie, to the honour of their recluſes and <hi>Monaſticall</hi> ſuperſtition. Their colour is ſlight, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing: becauſe (forſooth) our Saviour anſwering <hi>Peters</hi> queſtion, <hi>Maſter we have forſaken all, &amp;c. what ſhall wee have?</hi> ſaies, <hi>You ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones, and judge.</hi> But the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who had the mind of Chriſt, and the Spirit of God, and had beene once in heaven, hath enlarged the Commiſſion to all Saints,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. ver.<hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> even to theſe poore <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the moſt deſpiſed, and <hi>leaſt eſteemed</hi> among them: And therefore it is obſervable how he varies the perſon, and makes uſe of all the perſons in the plurall number; We, you, they. Not onely, <hi>Wee ſhall judge the Angels,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> which might be applyed to the Apoſtles, and no other; nor onely, <hi>You ſhall judge the world,</hi> or, <hi>The world ſhall be judged by you,</hi> which might exclude others, beſides the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> but, <hi>The Saints ſhall judge the world,</hi> in the words of our Text: <hi>Wee</hi> ſhall judge, <hi>you</hi> ſhall judge, all <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall judge the world. But S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſhall put it out of all queſtion, by the ancient Teſtimony of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord commeth with thouſands of his Saints,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jud. verſ. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Judgement upon all the ungodly, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Daniel</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59698:10"/>reckons to be thouſand thouſands, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand, even all his Saints. Even to the leaſt of all Gods Saints, is this honour given; how poorely, how baſely ſoever eſteemed of in this world, he ſhall be in <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to judge the world:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> They went about, ſome of them, in ſheepe-skinnes and Goat-skinnes, (not like Judges in skar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let) and yet, of them the world was not worthy, though they are accounted worthy to <hi>judge</hi> the world. The <hi>Romanes</hi> fetcht ſome from the plough, to the <hi>Dictatorſhip: Pharaoh</hi> tooke <hi>Joſeph</hi> out of priſon, to bee the ſecond in Egypt: <hi>David</hi> was ſent for, from the Sheepfolds, to bee annointed with Regall oile;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.71, 72.</note> 
                     <hi>As hee was following the Ewes</hi> (good Shepheard) <hi>he tooke him, that hee might feed Jacob his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Iſrael his inheritance.</hi> This is ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God fetches his <hi>Saints</hi> farther, even from the loweſt earth, to the higheſt heavens.<note place="margin">Pſal. 113.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee raiſeth up the poore out of the duſt, and lifteth up the needie out of the dung-hill; That he may ſet him with Princes, even with the Princes of his people; Such honour have all his Saints:</hi> and now I have done with the firſt part, of the three named, and paſſe on to the ſecond.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. The Matter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; To judge: wherein</note> The <hi>Commiſsion</hi> granted, or <hi>Matter</hi> of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>The Saints ſhall judge.</hi> There are, by Kings, ſeverall Commiſſions granted, not all alike honourable; Some, for inquirie upon lands; ſome, for charitable uſes; ſome, for matters of <hi>Niſi prius,</hi> as you call them; and perhaps many more, which I know not, nor much care to learne. That is the moſt eminent, which you call, <hi>A Commiſsion of Oyer and Terminer,</hi> which paſſes upon life and death; becauſe it concernes that which is moſt deere and precious in man, his <hi>Life.</hi> Gods preferments are ever like himſelfe, moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, moſt glorious, to the beſt and higheſt employments. If there be any <hi>Commiſsion</hi> weightier, either in honour, or execution, that ſhall be conferred upon his <hi>Saints: Doe you not know, that the Saints ſhall judge?</hi> and that with the Judgement of <hi>Condemnation?</hi> For explication of it, two things are to bee enquired; firſt, the <hi>Truth,</hi> and then the <hi>Time;</hi> the one in the ſenſe of the word, <hi>judge;</hi> the other
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59698:10"/> in the Tenſe of the Verbe, <hi>ſhall judge:</hi> wee follow both.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, the <hi>Truth</hi> of this Grant may well be ſcrupled;<note place="margin">1. The Truth of it; by a diſtinction.</note> How the Saints can be ſaid to <hi>judge;</hi> ſeeing firſt, wee have God himſelfe, (as well he may) taking this honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>God is Judge himſelfe, Pſal.</hi> 50.6. Secondly, granting a generall and univerſall <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to his Sonne, <hi>The Father hath committed all Judgement to the Sonne, even as,</hi> or <hi>becauſe he is the ſonne of man, Joh.</hi> 5.22 And thirdly, we have the Sonne diſcharging all from this Imployment, <hi>Judge not, that you be not judged, Math.</hi> 7.1. And yet here S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us of a <hi>Commiſsion</hi> of <hi>Judgement,</hi> granted to the <hi>Saints.</hi> For reconciliation of this, we muſt diſtinguiſh of Judgement, and Judges.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Judgement,</hi> which, for kind or manner,<note place="margin">1. Of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is</note> is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; as may appeare in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is <hi>Judicium Authoritatis:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Authoritatis.</note> the Judgement of Authoritie; which reſides in the King, as the roote and fountaine; and thus there is one onely <hi>Judge</hi> of the world, as one Lawgiver, <hi>God is judge himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Judicium Declarationis,</hi> by way of <hi>Declaration;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Declarationis.</note> and thus the booke of the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> may bee ſaid to <hi>Judge,</hi> becauſe they declare who, and how men are to be judged. And indeed, it is the <hi>Law</hi> that judges, not the Judge; hee doth but pronounce the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the Law. So ſaid they of old, <hi>Wee have a Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jus dicere, non jus dare.</note> 
                     <hi>and by our Law he ought to die. Doth our Law condemne a man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it heare him ſpeake?</hi> ſaid another. And thus, the <hi>Word</hi> of God, the booke of the Law, is ſaid to judge; <hi>The Word that I have ſpoken, ſhall judge you at the laſt day;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 12.48.</note> ſaid our Saviour.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Judicium Prolationis,</hi> by way of <hi>Pronunciation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Prolationis.</note> or paſſing of the <hi>Sentence:</hi> and this is done by the <hi>Judge</hi> alone, as our experience tels us. And in this ſenſe, Chriſt, as man, ſhall judge alone; <hi>All judgement is committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him;</hi> and hee ſhall pronounce that dreadfull ſentence, <hi>Goe you curſed, &amp;c.</hi> paſſing the finall <hi>doome</hi> upon the world.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59698:11"/> 4.<note place="margin">4. Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</note> 
                     <hi>Judicium Comparationis;</hi> by way of <hi>Compariſon,</hi> and thus not onely the Saints, but one wicked man, ſhall judge and condemne another.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chryſ. in locum.</note> So our Saviour tels ſome; <hi>Tyre and Sydon ſhall riſe in judgement with this generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and condemne it.</hi> And thus the Saints, not onely <hi>ſhall,</hi> but doe even <hi>now,</hi> judge the world. Their lives are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a living Law; their examples of <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> in the ſame temptations with other men, ſhall riſe up and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne</hi> the world, that followed not their patternes, in the ſame allowance of meanes.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. Approbationis</note> 
                     <hi>Aſſeſsionis, &amp; Approbationis</hi> (for I joyne them both together) by way of <hi>Aſſeſsion,</hi> and <hi>Approbation;</hi> as the <hi>Justices</hi> upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> doe ſit together with the Judge, and approve his Judgement. And thus, eſpecially, all the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall <hi>judge</hi> the world; They ſhall ſit upon Seats or Thrones, and approve, yea applaud the Sentence. <hi>The righteous ſhall rejoyce, when he ſees the vengeance, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Of Judges.</note> Of <hi>Judges,</hi> we may alſo diſtinguiſh; whereof there are ſeverall kinds, in a well ſettled ſtate.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. The King.</note> The <hi>King</hi> is the ſupreme Judge of all, within his owne Dominions, and God is Judge of all the world, by way of Authority.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. The Lord Chancellour.</note> The <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> is a generall deputed Judge, by <hi>Delegation</hi> from the King; the King himſelfe judgeth no man: ſo Chriſt, made the Great Lord Chancellour, or Lord Chiefe Juſtice of all the world, <hi>The Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all Judgement to the Sonne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. The twelve Judges, ſo called.</note> The twelve <hi>Judges</hi> are for their private <hi>Courts,</hi> or particular <hi>Circuits:</hi> and thus we may (perhaps) grant, the twelve Apoſtles, by ſpeciall <hi>Priviledge,</hi> ſhal judge the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. The Juſtices</note> All the <hi>Juſtices</hi> at their Quarter <hi>Seſsions</hi> are joynt-Commiſſioners; And thus againe the <hi>Saints,</hi> even all the Saints ſhall judge, in manner aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>I conclude this point, with that of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> with a little alteration:<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11, 12</note> 
                     <hi>Seeing</hi> theſe things are thus, <hi>what manner of perſons ought they to be, in all manner of holy Converſation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59698:11"/> and Godlineſſe, looking for, and hasting unto the comming of the Day of the Lord,</hi> when the Saints ſhall judge the world: For the Time is not yet, but ſhall ſhortly come, when the Saints <hi>ſhall</hi> judge; And that's the ſecond thing obſerved.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Time,</hi> or <hi>Date</hi> of this Commiſſion; It is not,<note place="margin">2. The Time: prorogued for two reaſons:</note> 
                     <hi>doe judge,</hi> for that is expreſſely forbidden, <hi>Judge not, &amp;c.</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſhall judge.</hi> It beares not date till the Great Day of <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> at the end of the world. It was the ſpeech of him, who is Lord of the Saints, yea <hi>King of Saints,</hi> when he was in this world, <hi>I came not to judge the world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 12.47.</note> 
                     <hi>but to ſave it.</hi> It is enough for the <hi>Saints</hi> to be like their Lord and Maſter; Hee came not to <hi>judge,</hi> but to be judged; but <hi>he aſcended into heaven, &amp;c. and from thence he ſhall come to judge the quicke and the dead,</hi> ſaies our <hi>Creed. God hath appointed a Day, wherein hee will judge the world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note> 
                     <hi>by that Man, whom hee hath appointed.</hi> Hee ſhall come openly among the Juſt,
<note place="margin">Veniet manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtè inter juſtos, judicaturus &amp;c.</note> to judge juſtly, who came ſecretly to bee judged by the Unjuſt, unjuſtly. Hee ſhall ſit as Judge, who ſtood before a Judge: Hee ſhall condemne the truly guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who was falſly accounted guiltie; as elegantly S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi> Even as hee was, ſo are his Saints in this world. They <hi>judge</hi> no man, their houre is not yet come; They are <hi>judged</hi> of all men, ſor this is the houre and day of the worlds <hi>Judgement.</hi> As theeves and malefactors, in the Gaole, doe ſometimes, in <hi>mockerie,</hi> repreſent the paſſages of an <hi>Aſsiſes;</hi> and there cite, arraigne, accuſe, condemne their <hi>Judges:</hi> So deale wicked men with Gods <hi>Saints,</hi> in this world. But the Day of <hi>Aſsiſes</hi> will come, when the <hi>Judges</hi> ſhall in earneſt condemne thoſe malefactors, who thus ſported themſelves with their owne deſtruction. <hi>The Saints ſhall judge,</hi> but not yet: And there are good reaſons of this <hi>Prorogation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and want of experience. There are many difficult and perplexed caſes,<note place="margin">1. Their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> which, what by reaſon of the <hi>ſubtiltie</hi> of wicked men, and what by the <hi>ſecrecie</hi> of the intentions of mens hearts, they are not able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59698:12"/> without danger of Errour: It was an intricate buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe propounded to young <hi>Salomon,</hi> that of the two har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, to find out the true mother of the childe, when no evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence could appeare on either ſide: And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>The Wiſdome of God was in him to doe Juſtice.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. King. 3.28.</note> I have read of a caſe ſometime propounded to the <hi>Areopagites,</hi> Judges amongſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Au. Gell. Noct. Allic. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> which, becauſe they could not well aſſoile, they wiſely commanded the parties to come againe an hundred yeare after, and they would doe them Juſtice: By that time, they thought, either they, the <hi>Judges,</hi> or the parties would be dead. To this purpoſe, may that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle fitly be applyed;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Judge nothing before the time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkeneſſe, and will make manifeſt the counſelſ of the hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Impotence of Affections.</note> Their <hi>Impotence,</hi> in regard of their <hi>Affections;</hi> too ſubject to paſſion and compaſſion: Feare, love, hatred, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pittie &amp;c. are able to corrupt the beſt <hi>Judgement.</hi> Our friends may perſwade us, our enemies may provoke us; the one to bee too favourable, the other to bee too harſh and cruell: I have read another ſtorie fitting to this purpoſe: <hi>In China,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. Hughen. Hiſt. Ind.</note> 
                     <hi>a part of the Indies, no man may rule, or beare any office of Juſtice in the Towne, or place, where he was borne; leſt his parents, or other friends, ſhould worke him to give ſentence of Judgement, contrary to the rules of equitie.</hi> And, I take it, it is the Cuſtome of this our Nation, that no <hi>Judge</hi> rides <hi>Circuit</hi> into that country where himſelfe dwels, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, for the very ſame reaſon. However, this wee know: This world is the home-towne of our <hi>Nativitie;</hi> wee live here among our friends, and among our enemies, who are many times, (too oft, God knowes) the <hi>ſnares</hi> of Juſtice: therefore, our God thinkes it fit to remove us from our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſoile, before hee imploy us in that ſtate-buſineſſe of <hi>Judgement.</hi> I conclude it, Let the cenſorious world spend it ſelfe in <hi>judging</hi> and condemning of the Saints; it is but mans <hi>Day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cor. 4.3.</note> as the Apoſtle cals it, but mans judgement, that may, and muſt be repealed; There will come the <hi>Day</hi> of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59698:12"/> the Lord, as the day of <hi>Judgement</hi> is called;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10.</note> yea the Day of the <hi>Saints</hi> will come; and then the courſe of things ſhall be cleane altered. The <hi>World</hi> now judges the <hi>Saints,</hi> then the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall judge the <hi>World;</hi> and that is the next, and laſt part.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Extent</hi> or latitude of the Commiſſion, the <hi>World.</hi> As Kings Commiſſions differ in their ſubject matter,<note place="margin">3. The Extent of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. The World, of</note> ſo alſo in their Extent; ſome are for one Towne or Citie; ſome for one or more Counties, the largeſt is but for their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. It is ſaid of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.16. 2. Chron. 19.5.</note> 
                     <hi>That he went from yeere to yeere in circuit to Bethel, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and judged Iſrael in all thoſe places.</hi> But afterwards this was divided amongſt many <hi>Judges,</hi> as wee may ſee in the time of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat:</hi> Yet, what if a mans <hi>Commiſsion</hi> reached over the whole Kingdome; what is that to the whole <hi>World,</hi> but a mole-hill to a mountaine? If further (which never yet was granted to one man) over the whole <hi>World,</hi> for one generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what is that to the innumerable generations paſt and to come? which yet are all ſubject to the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>Saints. Know you not that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi> The <hi>World</hi> hath diverſe acceptions in Scriptures; Here it is taken for the worſer part, the <hi>wicked</hi> men of the world, the <hi>unjuſt,</hi> in the 1. verſe, the <hi>Infidels</hi> in the 6. verſe,<note place="margin">1. Wicked men</note> as oppoſed to the <hi>Saints:</hi> not excluding, but rather including the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Angels,</hi> that is, the <hi>Divels;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Wicked An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, for three reaſons.</note> for ſo the Apoſtle addes in the next verſe, <hi>Know you not, that we ſhall judge Angels?</hi> The argument riſes by way of gradation, The <hi>Saints</hi> may well bee allowed to judge your leſſer matters of this life; for in the life to come, they ſhall judge the <hi>world</hi> of wicked men, nay more, they ſhall judge the wicked <hi>Angels. Such honour have all</hi> Gods <hi>Saints.</hi> Not to ſtand long: why might not Chriſt himſelfe alone judge them, and no more adoe? why ſhall the <hi>Saints</hi> judge both men and Angels? For three reasons:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To the greater <hi>torment</hi> and vexation of wicked men,<note place="margin">1. Vexation of Enemies.</note> and Divels, when they ſhall ſee thoſe very men, whom they ſcorned, oppreſſed, perſecuted, to bee now advanced, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59698:13"/> to Glory, but to bee their <hi>Judges.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Angels,</hi> who ſometime diſdained to be ſervants unto man,<note place="margin">Dolet Diabolus, quod ipſum &amp; Angelos ejus, Chriſti ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us ille peccator, ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicaturus eſt. Tertull de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. c.<hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> (as ſome think) that tempted, ſeduced, vexed man, ſhall now, to their further torment, ſee them gloriouſly advanced to be their <hi>Judges.</hi> Thoſe wicked men, who ſaid, as they to <hi>Lot,</hi> with much diſdaine; <hi>Hee came in as a ſtranger, and ſhall hee rule us?</hi> ſhall be moved, not more with griefe, than torment of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, to ſee them thus exalted over them; and that ſo much more, as they did more eſteeme them baſe and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: To find themſelves delivered over into the hands of their enemies, to be <hi>judged,</hi> of whom they can expect no mercy, what horrour muſt it needes breed in them? As if, when ſome Noble man or judge, had wronged ſome poore and meane man, the King ſhould deliver him over into the power of that man, to take his owne revenge: As <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>Hagar,</hi> to <hi>Sarah;</hi> and <hi>Joſuah</hi> thoſe heathen Kings to every common ſouldier, to ſet his feet upon their neckes: <hi>God ſhall tread Satan under your feete ſhortly;</hi> is promiſed to the <hi>Saints.</hi> To this purpoſe is that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the great advancement of the righteous, <hi>The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſhall ſee this,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.10.</note> 
                     <hi>and be grieved, hee ſhall gnaſh with his teeth</hi> (for indignation) <hi>and melt away.</hi> So our Saviour tels thoſe auditors of his, <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 13.27, 28.</note> 
                     <hi>when you ſhall ſee Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdome of heaven, and your ſelves thruſt out. Hell</hi> it ſelfe ſhould not bee perfect <hi>Hell,</hi> if the wicked ſhould not know, and ſee the <hi>Saints,</hi> whom they have abuſed, to bee thus <hi>glorious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Their owne Security.</note> For their owne greater <hi>Aſſurance</hi> &amp; <hi>Securitie;</hi> They ſhall not onely ſee a juſt retribution upon their enemies, men and divels, but have their owne voice, and hand in the excecution of it. They ſhall not neede to feare any more the perſecutions of wicked men, or the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying ſolicitations of wicked Angels; All their enemies ſhall be deſtroyed, and for their greater Securitie, <hi>When the ungodly ſhall periſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.8.</note> 
                     <hi>they ſhall ſee it with their eyes,</hi> and help
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59698:13"/> to act it with their owne hand. There ſhall bee a mutuall view of each other, in heaven, and hell: When the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are exalted, the ungodly ſhall ſee it: <hi>Dives</hi> as well ſees <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> as <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſees <hi>Dives</hi> in hell: and a gulfe is ſet between, that they can never come neere one another, either to comfort, or hurt one another any more.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For their greater <hi>Joy:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Joy.</note> Wee uſe to take wonderfull contentment and pleaſure in the miſery and deſtruction of thoſe, whom we eſteeme our enemies (though<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 24.17, 18.</note> ſinfully ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, I confeſſe, on earth) much more, if we may have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to <hi>revenge</hi> ourſelves upon them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.10</note> 
                     <hi>The righteous ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, when he ſeeth the vengeance, hee ſhall waſh his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps in the blood of the ungodly,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Pſalmiſt:</hi> and that without any the leaſt ſinne, in heaven; where God himſelfe ſhall <hi>laugh</hi> and <hi>mocke</hi> at the juſt condemnation of wicked and ungodly men.<note place="margin">Prov. 1.</note> I conclude all this firſt part with that ſpeech of the ſweet Singer of Iſrael, which, I thinke, was ſpoken by way of propheſie, of this very Day of the Saints Judgement. <hi>Let the Saints be joyfull in Glory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 149.5.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>let them ſing aloud upon their beds. Let the high praiſes of God bee in their mouthes, and a two edged ſword in their hands: To execute vengeance upon the heathen, and puniſhments upon the people: To bind their Kings in chaines, and their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in fetters of Iron: To execute upon them the vengeance, as it is written, Such honour have all his Saints. Doe you not know, that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now we are come to the ſecond Generall part of the Text, the <hi>Certaintie</hi> of this Dignitie of the <hi>Saints:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Part. The Certaintie: with</note> 
                     <hi>Doe you not know it?</hi> It fares with Gods <hi>Saints</hi> here, as with mens <hi>heires</hi> in their Minoritie: Though they be Lords of all, yet many yeeres paſſe, before they know their inheritance, or the Priviledges and honours thereof. God hath provided more for his <hi>Saints</hi> than they do know, than they can know: But yet, this they doe know, or may know, or muſt know, that the <hi>Saints,</hi> even they themſelves shall <hi>judge</hi> the world.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59698:14"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Rhetorick</hi> ſhewes the <hi>Divinitie;</hi> the Interrogation ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative makes it ſtrongly affirmative: You may know it, you doe know it, you muſt know it; for it is moſt <hi>uſefull</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> that all know it.<note place="margin">The Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> And ſo I will now make the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of all that hath been ſpoken in the former) part by way of <hi>Explication;</hi> which, of purpoſe, I have reſerved for the Concluſion. It is therefore very profitable for all parts, that it ſhould be knowne. Some things concerne the <hi>World,</hi> ſome the <hi>Saints,</hi> ſome both.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. To the world a double leſſon</note> The <hi>World</hi> (we begin with them) Let all wicked men know it, if they know it not already, that the <hi>Saints,</hi> whom they now ſcorn &amp; wrong ſhall one day be their <hi>Judges.</hi> Then</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Not to ſinne before them</note> Let them take heed how they <hi>ſinne</hi> before the <hi>Saints.</hi> They ſhall be their <hi>Judges,</hi> and dare they make them their <hi>witneſſes?</hi> That were a bold theefe, that durſt cut a purſe in the face and view of the Judge. A good conſideration, if men were not paſt wit, as well as grace, to reſtraine the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent looſeneſſe of profane men. If they feare not God, whom they ſee not, and therefore beleeve not that hee ſees them; yet let them reverence men, who ſee them, and whom they ſee. The preſence of ſome grave <hi>Senator</hi> hath this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">Si fortè quom c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em, &amp;c. Virg.</note> in a tumultuous multitude: when thoſe outrageous Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſaw the cheife Captaine, they left beating of <hi>Paul. Sanctitie</hi> ſhould make <hi>Impuritie</hi> bluſh, if it were not growne <hi>bloodleſſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 21.32.</note> 
                     <hi>Herod</hi> feared <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> becauſe hee was a <hi>Saint,</hi> a juſt man; what if he had known he ſhould one day be his <hi>Judge?</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> was but reaſoning of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>Temperance, and the Judgement to come,</hi> Felix <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled:</hi> yet little did he thinke his <hi>Judge</hi> was ſo nigh. They are worſe than <hi>Herod</hi> or <hi>Felix,</hi> who neither feare nor trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>ſinne</hi> before the <hi>Saints,</hi> who yet would be thought to know and beleeve this Scripture, <hi>That the Saints ſhall judge the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Not to wrong them.</note> Let them at leaſt take heed, how they <hi>wrong</hi> and abuſe the <hi>Saints.</hi> The <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall be their <hi>Judges,</hi> and dare they make them alſo their <hi>Accuſers? He reproved even Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, Touch not mine annointed, and do my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59698:14"/> no harme.</hi> Were not that <hi>malefactor</hi> mad or deſperate, that ſhould <hi>way-lay</hi> his Judge, and offer him injury, in words or deeds, as he was comming to the <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> or going towards the <hi>Judgement</hi> ſeat? what hope had he of any favour? <hi>Dives</hi> durſt not ſpeak a word to <hi>Lazarus</hi> (as we noted afore) whom he had but neglected, but intreats his Father <hi>Abraham</hi> for mercy. Heare it, all wicked oppreſſors, ſlanderers, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Gods <hi>Saints;</hi> you had as good, nay better, abuſe one of his Majeſties <hi>Judges,</hi> as wrong any, the pooreſt, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of Gods <hi>Saints.</hi> You have abuſed a <hi>Judge,</hi> yea your own <hi>Judge:</hi> Take it for good counſell, If you wil not be good your ſelves, yet hurt not thoſe that are good: Hurt them not? yea make them your friends (as men doe the Judges) by your unrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> and all the wayes you can, that they may ſpeake a good word for you upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> at that grand <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> when a friend in the <hi>Court</hi> will be worth more than all the mony in your purſes. At leaſt, I ſay, wrong them not, for certainly they muſt be your <hi>Judges. Agree with thine adverſary quickly whilſt thou art in the way with him leſt thy adverſary deliver thee to the Judge,</hi> is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Counſell: I ſay more, leſt thy <hi>Adverſary</hi> prove to bee thy <hi>Judge.</hi> For now you doe know, that <hi>the Saints ſhall judge the world.</hi> And ſo much for the <hi>World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Saints:</hi> Let them take notice of this certaine truth,<note place="margin">2. To the Saints a ground</note> this excellent priviledge; That they ſhall judge the <hi>world.</hi> It ſerves</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For a ground,<note place="margin">1. Of Patience</note> not onely of <hi>Comfort</hi> against thoſe hard preſſures, and great dejection, whereunto they are ſubjected in this world, but alſo of <hi>Patience,</hi> in the <hi>Cenſures</hi> and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world: as they that know their turne and time of <hi>Judgement</hi> is comming. See how confidently the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle contemnes the cenſures of men;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>With me it is a ſmall matter, that I ſhould be judged of you, or of mans judgement,</hi> mans <hi>Day,</hi> as the originall hath it. <hi>Let the ſame mind bee in you, that was in Chriſt Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.5.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>who humbled himſelfe to the death, even the death of the Croſſe:</hi> not onely to bee <hi>judged,</hi> but to <hi>die.</hi> Or as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> expreſſes it;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59698:15"/> 
                     <hi>Christ ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21.</note> He ſuffered himſelfe to be cenſured, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, mocked, crucified; but <hi>he ſhall come to judge both quick and dead:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.4.</note> 
                     <hi>When Chriſt, which is our life ſhall appeare, then ſhall you alſo appeare with him in glory,</hi> ſayes our Apoſtle. <hi>Behold the Lord commeth with thouſands of his Saints, to execute Judgement,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Jude: Be patient</hi> (and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table)
<note place="margin">Jam. 5.7.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>therefore brethren</hi> (they are S. <hi>James</hi> his words) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Judge ſtands before the doore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Of absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from their company.</note> For a <hi>Caveat</hi> againſt the <hi>Company</hi> of the wicked world; The <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall be their <hi>Judges,</hi> and doe they now make their <hi>companions? Have no fellowſhip with the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes of darkneſſe, but reprove them rather:</hi> How? by abſtaining from their companie, which is a reall reproofe, and a previous condemnation; <hi>Praejudicium aeterni judicii,</hi> as that Father in a like caſe, the <hi>praejudgement,</hi> of that eternall <hi>Judgement.</hi> How oft are they called upon for this? <hi>What fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quod eſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercium dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturis cum damnandis? Tertull.</note> 
                     <hi>God with Belial? &amp;c.</hi> what <hi>Commerce</hi> or ſocietie have <hi>Judges</hi> that muſt <hi>condemne,</hi> with malefactors, who are to be <hi>condemned,</hi> askes <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Know your ſelves (O you who profeſſe your ſelves <hi>Saints</hi>) know your worth and dignitie, with God: He purpoſes to make you his <hi>Judges</hi> of the world, and doe you make your ſelves equall to the <hi>world? Come out from among them, and touch no uncleane thing:</hi> Avoid their company, abandon their <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> as well as their <hi>faſhions:</hi> Be not partakers of their ſinnes, by too intire communion with them, leſt you be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their puniſhments. <hi>For</hi> (ſo addes <hi>Tertullian) unleſſe we now praejudge and praecondemne in them thoſe things, for which we ſhall then judge and condemne them, certainly they ſhall judge and condemne us.</hi> Let the <hi>Saints</hi> conſider it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Of Peace-making, both</note> For a ſtrong argument and motive to <hi>Peace-making</hi> on all hands: And this is indeed the principall ſcope of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; where it is worth the while to conſider, the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of the Apoſtle, in making one argument inferre a double concluſion; One in regard of the <hi>parties</hi> at variance, the other in regard of the <hi>Spectators</hi> that ſuffered them to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59698:15"/>goe to Law: For marke the words. In the firſt verſe he gives a ſharpe increpation to the <hi>parties</hi> going to Law, <hi>Dare any of you,</hi> (either plaintiffe or defendant) <hi>having a matter againſt another, go to law before the unjuſt, &amp; not before the Saints?</hi> Why not? might ſome man ſay. Why, <hi>doe you not know, the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi> how much more, leſſer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tters: But then, leſt thoſe that were <hi>beholders</hi> ſhould applaud themſelves as innocent, marke how he changes the words, in the latter part of the verſe, <hi>If then the world ſhall be judged by you, are you unworthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</hi> which cannot, in any reaſonable <hi>conſtruction,</hi> bee referred to the parties at variance, (it being utterly unfit, that men ſhould be their owne <hi>Judges</hi>) therefore hee ſecretly taxes them that were the <hi>by-ſtanders,</hi> for not interrupting their proceedings, by a wiſe and timely arbitrement; upon the ſame ground ſtill, <hi>Doe you not know that the Saints, even you, ſhall judge the world?</hi> we will apply it ſeverally, firſt to the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> then to the <hi>Spectators.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. To the <hi>parties</hi> litigant, or contending,<note place="margin">1. To the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> whether plaintiffe or defendant, it matters not. The Apoſtle would have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them <hi>goe to law,</hi> at leaſt before or under unbeleevers. Nay hee would have neither of them <hi>goe to law</hi> at all (as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerves not amiſſe) if the matter might, by any faire meanes, be ended by the <hi>Saints.</hi> For he doth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally blame them, not ſo much for going <hi>to Law</hi> before Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, as for not referring, their matters to a <hi>private</hi> deciſion; He doth not oppoſe Chriſtian Tribunals, to the Tribunals of Infidels, but publick lawing to private determination. My reaſons are; Firſt, there were no Chriſtian Magiſtrates, in thoſe times of the Church, but all Heatheniſh, and therefore he could not referre them, to ſuch as were not. Secondly, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, doth not onely ſignifie a publick <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> but oftentimes a private <hi>cenſure,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vide Bezam in locum.</note> as many inſtances would confirme, if we could ſtand upon it. To the point then: The <hi>parties</hi> at variance muſt not goe to Law, till their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren cannot end it. They muſt firſt <hi>referre</hi> it to their fellow <hi>Saints.</hi> This the Apoſtle urges upon them, by this argument,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59698:16"/> 
                     <hi>Doe you not know, &amp;c.</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Are the <hi>Saints</hi> ſo highly honored by God, to be made <hi>Judges</hi> of the world, and doe you think them unworthy to <hi>compoſe</hi> your leſſer diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences? <hi>There is therefore utterly a fault amongſt you,</hi> that you thus diſparage the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of heaven, the <hi>Saints;</hi> and expoſe not your ſelves only, but your profeſſion alſo, and the Profeſſors of the Goſpell, to the ſcorn and deriſion of the Infidels. For what will the heathen ſay? See how injurious, how malicious, how contentious theſe Chriſtians are! See how ſimple and ignorant they are! Not a man amongſt them that hath ſo much <hi>judgement</hi> or wiſdome, as to determine the leaſt difference that ariſes, but they muſt come to us for <hi>Judgement.</hi> We cannot, in our land (bleſſed be God) make that difference of Infidell and Chriſtian: but yet we have a diſtinction parallel to that, of Papiſts &amp; Proteſtants; Atheiſts and truly Religious. And this were argument ſufficient to a good heart, not to bring his differences into the publike eye of the world, till he had tryed all other meanes in vaine. For what will <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay? as of our Church differences, they doe ſay, Theſe are your <hi>Proteſtants; ut ſe invicem diligunt!</hi> See how they love, or rather hate and proſecute one another! What will <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and profane perſons ſay? Theſe are your <hi>Profeſſours,</hi> theſe are thoſe that would be called <hi>Saints,</hi> (as in the text) ſee how they fight, and warre, and devoure one another! See how ſimple and weake they are, that not a wiſe man amongſt them, to <hi>judge</hi> betweene his brethren! Why then, O why ſhould Chriſtians ſo diſparage one another, to thinke them unable or <hi>unworthy</hi> to judge their leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who are ſo farre honored by God, to be <hi>Judges</hi> of the world: and perhaps, when all is done, the buſineſſe fals into the hands of ſome, who are neither <hi>wiſe</hi> nor <hi>honeſt;</hi> who are of the world, and muſt one day be judged by the <hi>Saints?</hi> Let not, O let not then either <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> I ſay not, bee <hi>Judges,</hi> but nor <hi>Spectators</hi> nor <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of theſe unkind and <hi>unchriſtian</hi> quarrels. Referre them, referre them to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſmoother them in the firſt ſmoking. <hi>Doe you not,</hi> both parties, <hi>know that the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59698:16"/> 2. To the <hi>Spectators:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. To the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators.</note> The Apoſtle would have them both wiſe and willing, to undertake, if not the prevention, yet the ſpeedie concluſion of ſuch differences, betweene their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And the argument is as ſtrong for them: <hi>Doe you not know, &amp;c. If then the world ſhall be judged by you, are you unworthy to judge the ſmallest matters?</hi> Truly, my brethren, the disſhonour is greater, than you are aware of. If you bee <hi>willing</hi> but unable, it is your <hi>ſhame: I ſpeake it to your ſhame,</hi> (ſayes our Apoſtle) <hi>Is it ſo, that there is not a wiſe man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, no not one, that is able to judge between his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? but a brother goes to Law with a brother?</hi> If you be <hi>able,</hi> but unwilling, it is your <hi>blame,</hi> even want of a great deale of <hi>Pietie</hi> to God, and <hi>Charitie</hi> to your brethren. How can you think your ſelves able or worthy (willing I know you will be) to <hi>judge</hi> the world, that want either <hi>skill</hi> or <hi>will,</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> between your brethren? Be admoniſhed then (I ſpeake it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I hope, in a good time, to prevent many publike differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hereafter, though I expect no <hi>Fee</hi> for my <hi>Counſell</hi>) bee admoniſhed, I ſay, every man, to ſpend ſome time, ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſome paines, to repaire the firſt breaches of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns peace. Intreat them, beſeech them, adjure them, for their owne ſake, for peace ſake, for Religions ſake, for Gods ſake, to yeeld to a private determination. I conclude it: If peace be had, keepe it; if it be broken, every one, <hi>Plaintiffe, Defendant, Spectators,</hi> labour to repaire it. Live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you. That for the Saints.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To both, <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>world,</hi> as being mixt together;<note place="margin">3. To both the Saints and world:</note> and we have two things to propound unto them:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Moderation</hi> of their cenſures, in judging one another; How often, how earneſtly, are we called upon, to this purpoſe?<note place="margin">1. Not to judge one another.</note> 
                     <hi>Judge not, that you be not judged,</hi> ſayes our Lord &amp; Maſter.<note place="margin">Math. 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Judge nothing before the time,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Paul.</hi> What expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations the ſame Apoſtle makes for exceſſe in this particular? <hi>Who art thou, that judgeſt another mans ſervant?<note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.10.</note> Why doſt thou judge thy brother? and why doeſt thou ſet at naught thy brother?</hi> why doſt thou <hi>vilifie,</hi> or as <hi>Tertullian</hi> expreſſes the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59698:17"/>ſense of that word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, why doſt thou <hi>Nullifie</hi> thy brother? Yet as if the day of <hi>Judgement</hi> were come already, we are all <hi>Judges</hi> one of another. It is a <hi>world</hi> of wonder to ſee, how the world is made one common <hi>Tribunal,</hi> where every man aſcends the <hi>Throne,</hi> or place of Judgement, and there arraignes, accuſes, and condemnes his brother. At leaſt we keepe our turnes. Now we judge others; then others get up and judge us, as if we were all Judges, and all delinquents. Amongſt our ſelves, we may divide all into two <hi>Claſſes,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and Religious, but both agree, or rather, diſagree in Judgement. The looſe and <hi>Profane</hi> perſons judge all men, more ſtricter, and preciſer then themſelves, mad, fooliſh, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuperſtitious, in a word (the worſt they can ſay) <hi>hypocrites.</hi> On the other ſide, thoſe that are ſtrictly, &amp; would be thought truly <hi>Religious,</hi> diſcharge as faſt at them; Papiſts, Atheiſts, profane, wicked; yea (which I tremble to thinke on) <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</hi> Good Lord, whither will our indiſcreet <hi>zeale,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous raſhneſſe carry us. O men and brethren forbeare, forbeare: who made you <hi>Judges</hi> in this world? when thy Saviour would not be a Judge in a caſe of <hi>Niſi prius,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide an <hi>Inheritance,</hi> but refuſed it, upon this very reaſon, <hi>Man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>who made me a Judge or a divider betwixt you;</hi> how dareſt thou be ſo bold, as to <hi>judge</hi> of life and death, and that <hi>eternall,</hi> of the ſoule? Suppoſe you ſhall be <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> yet not in this <hi>World.</hi> Will you anticipate, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date your Commiſſion? Wicked men are meere uſurpers; they are to be judged, not to judge at all. The <hi>Saints,</hi> are too precipitate, to ſtart up into the <hi>Judgement</hi> ſeat, (as <hi>Abſalom</hi> into his Fathers <hi>Throne</hi> before his death) before the Time. I ſay to both, <hi>Judge not</hi> now, <hi>that you be not judged</hi> for your labour.<note place="margin">Jam. 4.11.</note> 
                     <hi>Speake not evill one of another, brethren; he that ſpeaketh evill of his brother and judgeth his brother, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth evil of the Law, and judgeth the Law: but if thou judge or condemne the Law, thou art not a doer of the Law, but a Judge:</hi> they are S. <hi>James</hi> his words, and not mine: S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhall cloſe up this point: <hi>Judge nothing before the time, till the Lord come;</hi> till the day of Judgement.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59698:17"/> 2. A ſtrong enforcement for <hi>Holineſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. To ſtudie Holineſſe.</note> that thus qualifies a man to make him a <hi>Judge</hi> of the world. The Apoſtle ſhall ſpeake what I intend, fully to my foregoing diſcourſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Follow peace with all men,</hi> (heare it Plaintiffe, Defendant, and Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators) <hi>and Holineſſe,</hi> (heare it all men) <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> without which, no man ſhall ever be a <hi>Judge</hi> in heaven, what ever he be on earth. Labour above all things for <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> they that want it, to procure it; they that have it, to increaſe it; <hi>Doe you not</hi> now <hi>know, that the Saints, that is the Holy Ones, and they onely, ſhall judge the world? O you Sonnes of men, how long will you have ſuch pleaſure in vanity, and ſeeke after lyes? Know you that the Lord hath choſen to himſelfe the man that is godly,</hi> the man that is holy, to make a Judge of in heaven: How long, O you profane ones, you <hi>ſcoffers</hi> and deriders of <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> will you deſpiſe and ſcorne that which muſt bee your Judge? Kings chuſe <hi>Judges</hi> chiefly for their <hi>knowledge</hi> and experience; God chuſes his by conſcience and <hi>Holineſſe.</hi> If theſe two muſt be ſevered, God ſayes, Let me have the man that hath more <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and leſſe <hi>Science;</hi> rather than him, that hath all <hi>Science</hi> and no <hi>Conſcience:</hi> Come then, my brethren, come to the <hi>Innes</hi> of <hi>Court,</hi> theſe <hi>Courts</hi> of Gods houſes, and ſtudy <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> more than knowledge, that you may be accounted worthy, to be made Judges of the world. Knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Holineſſe</hi> may make a man a <hi>Judge</hi> indeed, but not of the <hi>world,</hi> but of <hi>Himſelfe:</hi> Such a man, is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſelfe-judged,</hi> ſelfe-condemned, to ſave the <hi>Judges</hi> a labour. <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is the very <hi>Seale</hi> of our Commiſſion; or at leaſt the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> written round about it, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chrys. in <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>2.19.</hi>
                     </note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in a like caſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.20. The Apoſtle tels us ſo: <hi>The foundation of God ſtands ſure, and hath this ſeale, The Lord knoweth who are his:</hi> but that is the <hi>privie Seale.</hi> The <hi>broad Seale</hi> is that which followes, <hi>Let every one that cals upon the Name of the Lord, depart from iniquitie;</hi> that is, Let him be <hi>Holy.</hi> If any man pretend a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for this <hi>Judicature,</hi> and it want this <hi>Inſcription,</hi> it is a counterfeit, and meerely forged. This <hi>Holines</hi> is the thing which God eſteemes above
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59698:18"/>all things in his <hi>Judges;</hi> and which, above all things, as we ſaid at firſt, makes <hi>God</hi> himſelfe a competent <hi>Judge</hi> of the world. And thus he requires and expects his <hi>Judges</hi> ſhould be qualified withall, above all his other <hi>Attributes:</hi> not that they ſhould be like him, in <hi>Power, Wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c. But in <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Be you Holy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.26.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>as I am Holy: Be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> Nay, (if we may, as we may, beleeve S. <hi>Paul) Not many wiſe, not many noble, not many mightie, are called</hi> out to this preferment: <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe: and the weake things of the world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. here.</note> 
                     <hi>to confound the things that are mightie: and baſe things of the world, and things that are deſpiſed, hath God choſen</hi> to make his <hi>Judges</hi> of. Covet you the beſt thing then, and that is <hi>Holineſſe.</hi> Let others ſcoffe at <hi>Holineſſe:</hi> Let others be <hi>Ambitious</hi> for honour, for knowledge, for wealth, for pleaſure: but, if you will heare my Counſell and advice, be you covetous, ambitious, zealous for <hi>Holineſſe.</hi> One grain of true <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſhall advance you higher with God, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than a whole world of <hi>greatneſſe</hi> without it. When I have prayed for you in the Apoſtles words, I ſhall have done, and be no further tedious: <hi>Now the very God of peace, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie you throughout,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 5.23.</note> 
                     <hi>and I pray God, that your whole Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Soules and bodies, may be kept blameleſſe, till the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that is, till the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the great and grand <hi>Aſſiſes,</hi> and then you ſhall ſee the difference between the Righteous and the Wicked,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not; between the <hi>Holy</hi> and profane; Then ſhall it be manifeſt to all the world, that the <hi>Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> onely, ſhall <hi>judge</hi> the world. Now to the <hi>King of Saints,</hi> the <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy</hi> God, be aſcribed of us, and of all his <hi>Saints,</hi> as is moſt due, all <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and honour, all might and Majeſty, all Power and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from henceforth and for ever.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:18"/>
                  <p>'ΕΠΙΧΑΙΡΕΚΑΚΙΑ. OR, A CLOSE HYPOCRITE DISCOVERED. As it was delivered in a Sermon, by <hi>D.C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. COR. 13.6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Love rejoyceth not in iniquity, but rejoyceth together with the Truth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.Y.</hi> for <hi>Ph. Nevill,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gun in Ivie-lane. 1641.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:19"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59698:19"/>
                  <head>'ΕΠΙΧΑΙΡΕΚΑΚΙΑ. OR, A CLOSE HYPOCRITE DISCOVERED.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>LUKE 18.11.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, unjuſt, adulterers, or even as this Publicane.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T matters not ſo much ſometimes what,<note place="margin">1. The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> as with what mind men ſpeake. When <hi>Judas</hi> ſaid, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ointment powred upon our Saviours head, <hi>What meanes all this waſte?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 12.5, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>This ointment might have been ſold, and given to the poore;</hi> the words were ſeemingly very charitable, but the mind was nothing leſſe, in the judgement of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt, who knew him better then we: <hi>This he ſpake,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59698:20"/>not becauſe he cared for the poore, but becauſe he was a theefe.</hi> The very like to this, is obſervable in this preſent ſpeech of the Phariſee: For who, that lookes at the words mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, without reſpect to the mind and intention of him that ſpake it, would not take him, not onely for a good and honeſt, but alſo for a very pious &amp; devout man; who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo thankfull, and 2. thankfull for ſuch a mercy, as few men take notice of, or acknowldege any favour, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>hee is not ſo bad as other men?</hi> Many indeed (being more ſenſible of corporall, then ſpirituall mercies) ſeem thankfull that they are not ſo miſerable, ſick, poore, and as other men; But few, beſide this Phariſee (or thoſe that are truly godly) give thankes to God, they are not ſo bad or ſinfull as other men. But he that knew the heart, better then wee the words, hath diſcovered that which we durſt not have cenſured, that this ſo glorious-ſeeming a ſentence proceeded from a deep and groſſe hypocriſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For both the Evangeliſt, in his preface to the Parable, hath told us, that his alme and end was naught; partly to juſtifie himſelfe and partly to vilifie others, with proud ſcorning and deſpiſing of them; <hi>He ſpake this Parable to certaine that truſted in themſelves, that they were righteous, and deſpiſed others:</hi> And alſo our bleſſed Saviour, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maker, hath informed us of the iſſue (no doubt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his intention) that God rejected this his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thankfulneſſe; The poore Publicane went away juſtified, and not the Phariſee.</p>
                  <p>The words then (you ſee) may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> waies be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered:<note place="margin">2. The Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> either abſolutely in themſelves; and ſo they are very good: and beſide other good things in them, this is not the leaſt, that he is thankfull (or at leaſt thought he ought to be thankfull) for this <hi>privative</hi> or negative mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that he was not ſo bad as other men: Or elſe reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, with regard to the man, or the mind of him that spake them, and ſo they are very bad; as bad almoſt as can be, even an intimation of a kind of Diabolicall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing</hi> at others badneſſe; as if hee would thanke God,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59698:20"/>there was ſcarce an honeſt man in the world but he;<note place="margin">Quid eſt cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri homines, niſi omnes praeter ipſum? Ego, inquit, juſtus ſum, cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. <hi>Auguſt. de Verb. Dom. ſerm.</hi> 36.</note> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a kind of complacence and contentment in their ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for ends hereafter to be ſpecified. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hath a ſpeech ſomething like this, but with a great deale of difference in the intention of the ſpeaker, when he thus writes to his Romans,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note> 
                     <hi>God be thanked, that ye were the ſervants of ſinne; but ye have obeyed from the heart the forme of doctrine to which yee were delivered:</hi> Hee doth not give God thankes, that they were, or had been the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of ſinne; that were impious for the Apoſtle to doe, or us to thinke: but that having been the ſervants of ſin, they had now <hi>obeyed the forme of doctrine delivered to them.</hi> Had this Phariſee thanked God, that he was better then other men; or not ſo bad as other men, with a ſimple and humble mind, he had been worthily to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but when as he doth this with a proud and ſcornfull mind: he ſeems to be glad, and pleaſed, that others were ſo bad, and ſo much worſe then himſelfe: And this we may obſerve, That we well cannot (or ſeldome doe) give thankes for that, wherein we doe not ſomewhat joy and take delight. Little joy makes cold thankes; but as thankfulneſſe increaſes joy, ſo joy produces thankfulneſs. Now that a man ſhould ſpend his joy or thankes for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers badneſſe is a wickedneſſe incident to none but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh diſpoſitions; and this, we think, was juſtly taxable in this Phariſee.</p>
                  <p>To handle the words in both theſe reſpects,<note place="margin">3. The Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> the time will not permit; we will therefore looke upon them in the ſecond conſideration, with reſpect to the mind of the ſpeaker, as it is diſcovered to us; and occaſionally take in ſuch points of the former, as doe, or may pertaine to the application of the latter. The point of obſervation will be this, [That <hi>Whatever ſhewes of goodneſſe an hypocrite may make, yet he is ſecretly glad, and takes delight in others badneſſe:] God, I thanke thee, I am not as other men are, &amp;c.</hi> which is a kind of triumph or inſultation over other mens infirmities, and eſpecially over the poore Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59698:21"/>who was reputed one of the chiefe ſinners of thoſe times, and moſt odious and infamous. Now had the Phariſee onely looked at his owne credit (as no doubt in part he did look at it) he would not have compared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with men ſo notoriouſly bad: For what honour or excellency is it, for a man not to be ſo naught as a Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can? eſpecially for a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> whoſe profeſſion was moſt eminent in thoſe times? It had been better in ſuch an intention, to have left out this clauſe, and to have told of his owne extraordinary perfections, as after he doth, <hi>I faſt twice in the weeke, I give tithes of all I doe poſſeſſe.</hi> But making ſuch a compariſon, in ſuch a manner, diſcovers a naughty diſpoſition of a ſoule, that did pleaſe it ſelfe with others badneſſe, or being worſe then himſelfe: This cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of heart, is more groſſely manifeſted by ſome, who do openly make themſelves merry with other mens infirmities:
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.23.</note> The foole (<hi>Solomons</hi> wicked foole) counts it a ſport to commit wickedneſſe; not only himſelfe, but to ſee others do ſo too; as to heare men ſweare, or curſe, or fret, &amp;c. An hypocrite doth the ſame, though more cloſely; he ſeemes to thanke God, that he is not ſo bad as others, when indeed he is glad others are not ſo good as he. The contrary whereof appeares in thoſe that are truly good, As they deſire others goodneſs, <hi>I would to God all the Lords people could propheſie, &amp;c.</hi> ſo they take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſeeing and hearing others vertues, and thanke God that others are better then themſelves; as we may heare hereafter: But to manifeſt the truth of our Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation before propounded, we have examples of other hypocrites,<note place="margin">1. By Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> who were of the ſame diſpoſition: Firſt, in thoſe counterfeit Viſitants of <hi>David, In mine adverſity they rejoyced and gathered themſelves together:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 35.15, 16.</note> So we reade it; but the word in the originall ſignifies, <hi>in claudicatione mea,</hi> In my halting they rejoyced; which is<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi rend="sup">a</hi>. Heb. 12.13.</note> applied to the ſoule ſometimes, as well as to the body: and ſo may ſignifie as well the evill of ſinne, as that of puniſhment. <hi>David</hi> being put upon hard adventures, by <hi>Sauls</hi> perſecution,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59698:21"/>ſometimes was ſubject to haltings, that is, to failings, and the diſcovery of many infirmities: Theſe, when ſome heard or ſaw, they gathered themſelves together, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at it, made themſelves merry with it, though they would ſeem to him to be very ſorry; and comming to viſit him, would teare their clothes, and expreſſe much griefe; as <hi>Tremellius</hi> underſtands the words. But now, who were the men that did thus? The next Verſe tells you that, <hi>Hypocriticall mockers at feaſts,</hi> that is, men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that diſſembled much religion, but were but ſtarke hypocrites, the good fellowes of thoſe times, that had many joviall and merry meetings; and when they were aſſembled together, they dealt with <hi>David,</hi> as the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines did in a like caſe with <hi>Sampſon</hi> (ſent for him to make them ſport) made him, and his infirmities, his hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, their <hi>Table-talke;</hi> mocking, and making jeſts upon him: <hi>Hypocriticall mockers at feaſts.</hi> And this <hi>David</hi> having former experience of, he feares and prayes againſt in another place: <hi>I ſaid, Heare me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>leſt my enemies rejoyce over mee; when my foot ſlippeth, they magnifie themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: For I am ready to halting,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Ainſwor. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> to ſhew my infirmities, in my tryalls and afflictions. And upon this ground hee enforces his ſupplication, for ſtrength and grace; becauſe his hypocriticall enemies would vaunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and triumph in his failings. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> had experience of the like in his times;<note place="margin">Jerem. 20.10.</note> 
                     <hi>They waited</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for my halting; peradventure hee will be enticed, and wee ſhall prevaile againſt him, &amp;c.</hi> There were ſome that wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Prophet, to ſee if they could catch him in ſome untruth; and to this purpoſe, they laid baits to entice him, and ſnares to entrap him, that ſo they might have occaſion to inſult over him, that <hi>Jeremy</hi> himſelfe was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken napping, as well as others: And who were the men that did thus watch him? <hi>All my familiars</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the men of my peace;</hi> hypocrites, that would come to enquire of him, what was the word of the Lord; <hi>Report, ſay they, and we will report it:</hi> Falſe Prophets would come to him,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59698:22"/>pretending they waited upon him, and depended upon him, as a true Prophet of God; but the truth was, they waited for his halting, that ſo they might triumph over him, that he was as much overtaken as themſelves: which argues, That <hi>Hypocrites, however ſeemingly good, yet ſecretly they take delight and contentment in others infirmities, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. By reaſon.</note> which being a naughty diſpoſition, and a divel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, you may wonder it ſhould be incident to any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable living man: we will therefore ſee the grounds hereof.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Reaſon, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: for it is</note> a corrupt heart finds comfort in company: It is true of ſinne, as well as of miſery, <hi>Solamen miſeris ſocios habuiſſe.</hi> It is not ſo with good hearts; they care not how many companions they have in good, how few in evill, either of ſinne or puniſhment: <hi>Let thy hand, I pray thee, be againſt mee, and againſt my fathers houſe: as for theſe ſheep, what have they done?</hi> Contrarily, the Harlot having her owne childe dead, would be contented to have her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to be dead too; this would be a kind of comfort and contentment to her. Juſt ſo it is in ſin with naughty hearts, they comfort themſelves in others ſinfulneſſe; and they have it from their father the Divell: So ſoone as he had ſinned, and was hurled downe to hell; his next worke was to entice man, and make him ſinfull, ſo to make him alſo miſerable: But what comfort can a man take in wicked company?</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. A foile to his ſeeming good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> It will make a <hi>foile</hi> for his ſeeming goodneſſe; others badneſſe, oppoſed againſt his goodneſſe, makes him ſeeme better, as his goodneſſe makes others to ſeem worſe: as blacke and white oppoſed, make each other appeare more eminent in their kind: A Sun-burnt face is white, compared with a Black-moore. The Phariſee was a Saint to the Publicane: And this was the very intent of the Phariſee, to bring in theſe examples of the groſſeſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to make himſelfe ſeeme more gloriouſly vertuous. <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith was ſublimated and exalted, by the infidelity of thoſe times: The chaſtity of <hi>Lot</hi> was more ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59698:22"/>that, like a precious pearle, it lay in the dunghill of filthy Sodome: As their ſinne was aggravated, and, if I may ſo ſay, magnified, by the oppoſition of <hi>Lots</hi> chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. An hypocrite, ſuch as this Phariſee was,<note place="margin">Animal gloriae.</note> is a vain-glorious creature, ſeeking by all meanes to magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and therefore glad to fetch luſtre to his ſeeming vertues from others vices: Yea, <hi>Genus virtutis eſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Salvian.</note> 
                     <hi>eſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vitioſius,</hi> ſayes one; It is held a kind of vertue and honour in bad times, to be leſſe vicious: And with ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple judgements, he paſſes for a juſt man, that is no extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, or oppreſour; hee very chaſte, that is no groſſe adulterer: This the hypocrite knowes; and therefore if he can produce examples of affirmative or <hi>poſitive</hi> illneſs, ſuppoſes he ſhall find the honour, at leaſt of a <hi>privative</hi> or negative goodneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he cannot attaine this,<note place="margin">2. A cover of his badneſſe.</note> to get a colour to varniſh his ſeeming goodneſſe, yet to find a cover for his owne badneſſe will be a comfort: He is not now without an excuſe, to extenuate at leaſt his owne knowne badneſſe: I am a ſinner indeed, but not ſo bad as ſuch and ſuch; not as other men are, extortioners, adulterers, &amp;c. men of good note, and better parts, have done worſe then ever I did: I am no extortioner, I thanke God; I am no adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer: and this is the common plea of ignorant people, I thanke God, I am neither whore nor theefe, as ſuch and ſuch are; and ſo pleaſe themſelves, and comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they are not ſo bad as others are: and this is the uſe they make of others badneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This gives them hope of a good condition,<note place="margin">3. A ground of vaine hope.</note> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their wicked lives: they hope they may be ſaved as well, yea before others, that are worſe then they in ſome particulars, eſpecially if they be men that have had the reputation of godlineſſe. <hi>David</hi> committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery and murder, <hi>Noah</hi> was drunke, ſo was <hi>Lot,</hi> and inceſtuous; many profeſſours now are worſe over-ſeen then they are, they thanke God: yet theſe men were (at leaſt hoped to be) ſaved; they lived and died Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59698:23"/>and why may not they doe ſo with leſſer ſinnes? This is the common deluſion of ignorant men; If they be not ſaved that are no extortioners, no adulterers, &amp;c. what will become of thoſe that are? they hope to ſcape as well as they.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. A cloake of ſhame.</note> This will ſerve to allay the diſcredit, and <hi>ſhame</hi> of their owne wicked courſes; ſingularity in ſin makes men more remarkable, and ſo more infamous: community either makes it eſteemed no fault, or no crime; <hi>Incipit eſſe licitum, quod incipit eſſe publicum,</hi> That begins to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted lawfull, which begins to be publick: And that ceaſes to be <hi>ſhamefull,</hi> that moſt or many doe. For this cauſe a ſinner deſires to infect others, if hee can, or at leaſt is glad to find them infected, to qualifie his owne ſhame.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. Fellowſhip in miſery.</note> Laſtly, if in none of theſe he can take any comfort, yet in this he will, that he ſhall not be miſerable alone: This we heare deſperately out of the mouthes of wicked men, If they doe goe to hell , they ſhall not goe alone; company good ſtore: Miſerable comforters are they all; yet ſuch comfort the corrupt hearts of men (as the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himſelfe alſo does) ſucke out of the falls and ſinnes of other men: And this is the firſt reaſon of their joy in evill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. Reaſon, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie.</note>Another reaſon is, that ſecret envie, which is the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant of hypocriticall pride: <hi>Doe you thinke the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayes in vaine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſpirit that is in us lusteth after envie,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>James?</hi> There is in every proud heart a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of envie, the nature whereof is, as <hi>to grieve at others good, ſo to rejoyce at others bad;</hi> whether of ſin, or miſery: <hi>The ungodly ſhall ſee it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.10.</note> that is, the proſperity of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>and it ſhall grieve him.</hi> Now this is certaine, He that <hi>grieves</hi> at anothers good, will <hi>rejoyce</hi> at his hurt or evill: And this is as true in morall good or evill, He that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, and conſequently grieves at anothers vertues or goodneſſe (as every hypocrite doth, he would have none thought vertuous but himſelfe) will certainly be glad,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59698:23"/>and much pleaſe himſelfe with others badneſſe; becauſe (as we ſaid) this addes a luſtre to his ſeeming vertues. A proud man cannot endure a competitour in goodneſſe: The Phariſees did all they could to engroſſe the name and honour of knowledge and religion to themſelves; and therefore, when our bleſſed Saviour was deſervedly raiſed and magnified by the people above them, his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was the object of their envie, &amp; the matter of their torment and vexation: And when they had procured him to be put to death, how did they rejoyce and inſult upon him! The like may be ſeen of <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.</p>
                  <p>A third and laſt reaſon is,<note place="margin">3. Reaſon, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> from a ſecret hatred of goodneſſe, however he may ſeem to love and favour it. An hypocrite, what ſhewes ſoever he make, yet loves not goodneſſe; not in himſelfe, much leſſe in others. The appearance indeed he loves, becauſe it brings him credit in the world; but he <hi>receives net the truth in the love of it:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> Yea, ſecretly he hates it, and hates to be reformed, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes; and no marvell: for hee hates God, though perhaps he doth not perceive it. Now this is a rule, As Love and Hatred are contrary affections, ſo they have contrary objects: Love good, and hate evill; or love evill, and hate good. Againe, as they that love good in themſelves or others, cannot but joy and delight in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding it; ſo they that hate good, cannot but rejoyce in the evill of others. A good man is pleaſed as well with others good, as his owne: An evill man no leſſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers illneſſe, then his owne. <hi>Love</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>rejoyces not in iniquity, but</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>rejoyceth in the truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.6.</note> or with the truth: <hi>Love</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>envieth not, it ſwelleth not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>it vaunteth not it ſelfe</hi> (over others infirmities) <hi>it behaveth not it ſelfe unſeemly:</hi> but Hatred envies, ſwells, or is puffed up, vaunts it ſelfe, and behaves it ſelfe unſeemly; and thereupon rejoyces in iniquity: Theſe are the grounds of the point.</p>
                  <p>And now we come to make ſome Application<note place="margin">4. The Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that</note> of this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59698:24"/>Doctrine to our ſelves; and we will (for better method and memory) reduce all we have to ſay to two heads: 1. The <hi>diſcovery</hi> of many for hypocrites, by the wrong uſes they make of others infirmities, or ſinfulneſſe. 2. The <hi>directions</hi> to the right uſes that wee ſhould make.</p>
                  <p>The firſt uſe hereof is,<note place="margin">1. For diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of manifold hypocriſie, as</note> to uſe it as a light to diſcover a world of hypocrites, who by ſeverall waies doe manifeſt this naughty and curſed diſpoſition, to rejoyce or take delight in others badneſſe; and they are of many ſorts: We will note ſome:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſuch as, from the ſight and knowledge of others ſinnes, take occaſion to harden themſelves in their ſinfull courſes, and to ſtrengthen themſelves in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; comforting themſelves in the company of others, and perhaps thoſe of the better ſort, as they are reputed; and ſo <hi>ſettle themſelves upon their dregges,</hi> as <hi>Zephany</hi> ſpeakes: Why (ſay they) many of the beſt of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have been ſubject to their faults and infirmities; done as bad, or worſe perhaps then we, and yet were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: <hi>Noah, David, Lot,</hi> and others in our owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. But to diſcourage this concluſion, we propound to ſuch a threefold conſideration.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The difference between them and their copy: For, 1. they ſinned of infirmity, theſe men of deliberation: They did not look at the examples of others that fell before them, to fall after them, which theſe men doe: They purpoſed, reſolved, ſwore they would keep Gods commandements; ſo did never theſe: therefore theirs were ſinnes of infirmity, theſe of preſumption. 2. They ſinned, but they repented, and proportionably to their ſinne; <hi>David</hi> watered his couch with his teares; <hi>Peter</hi> wept bitterly; did not, as theſe men doe, comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and put off ſorrow, with examples of others fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And, 3. they ſinned, but not after repentance; <hi>Noah</hi> drunke but once, &amp;c. theſe never repent; or if they ſeem to doe ſo, it was but in hypocriſie, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59698:24"/>in their ſin, by others examples, doth demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The iſſue and ſucceſſe of thoſe ſinners, whom they preſume to follow: They ſinned, but they ſmarted ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; none ſo ſharply out of hell: <hi>David</hi> had not only the ſword threatned without, but had his bones broken within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. If they knew how deare they paid for their ſinnes, they would be loth to buy the pleaſure at ſo deare a rate; content not therefore your ſelves with this poore comfort of their examples.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This would alſo be conſidered by ſuch men, that this is a moſt fearfull perverting of the Scripture, and the providence of God, in ſuffering others to fall before our eyes, to their owne deſtruction, as the Apoſtle ſayes ſome men doe; and amongſt all the uſes that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends therein, this is the worſt and moſt dangerous: For if we aske, Why did God ſuffer his children heretofore to fall into foule and ſcandalous ſinnes, and record them in the Scripture? One of theſe three may be ſaid: Firſt, for admonition; <hi>Theſe things were written for our admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we ſhould not luſt as they luſted,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> 
                     <hi>nor murmure as they murmured; let him therefore that thinkes he ſtands, take heed leſt he fall.</hi> Secondly, for <hi>comfort,</hi> that thoſe that fall by infirmity, or otherwiſe, might have a ground of hope to riſe againe; Who ſhould ever riſe, if they had not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len? How apt are men, through their owne corruption, and the Divels temptations, to deſpaire? None of Gods children ever fell ſo low, ſo foulely, would he ſay: Yes, <hi>Paul</hi> was a perſecutour, &amp;c. and received to mercy,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.16.</note> that God might in him ſhew an example, as of humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo of Gods mercy: Or thirdly, God in his providence ſuffers theſe falls, in former and preſent times, to make <hi>ſtumbling blockes</hi> for ſome, whom he purpoſes to deſtroy, to keep them from coming into the way of godlineſſe; and ſo from the end, to which it leads, eternall life: Its certaine, many doe <hi>ſtumble</hi> at this ſtone, and rocke of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the fallings and failings of Gods people; and are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59698:25"/>either ſet at a ſtand in the profeſſion of Religion, as the people ſtood ſtill at <hi>Aſahels</hi> carkaſſe; or elſe turne quite backe againe, as if that were not the way, which ſuch men walke in; who fall many times more hainouſly, more ſcandalouſly then meere naturall men: They will not in ſad and ſerious manner profeſſe, becauſe ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Religion, and are not; <hi>Woe be to them, by whom the offence cometh:</hi> but woe alſo to the world, becauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; woe to the giver, and woe to the taker of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. The way to heaven is a narrow and a ſtraight way, and beſides, ſlippery; he is more then a man, that falls not ſometimes, having ſo many ſtumbling blockes laid in his way by the fleſh, the world, and the Divell: but theres no other way but that. Now were not he a mad man, that would refuſe to walke a ſlippery way, ſuppoſe over ice, ſeeing there is no other way; becauſe he ſees many ſlip before him? Yet he is worſe, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his neighbour downe, will not ſtep over him, but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſtumble, and fall with him; and then plead his example, to excuſe his owne falling: Thus do many men comfort themſelves in the falls of others; and theſe are the firſt ſort.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, another ſort of hypocrites are thoſe that, from the ſight or knowledge of others ſinnes, take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to vent their gall againſt Religion, and the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it ſelfe; to lay all the fault upon that, and to inſult over the whole number of them that profeſſe it; <hi>This is their Religion, Theſe are your Profeſſours, your Holy ones, thus they doe ſuch they are all: Fie upon this Faction;</hi> as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſaid of <hi>David, Fie upon thee, fie upon thee, we have ſeen it with our eyes:</hi> Or, as ſome ſaid of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the ring-leader of the Nazarenes, as one called him: Away with him, away with him, it is not fit that he ſhould live: But to coole this heat a little, conſider,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What hard <hi>meaſure</hi> theſe men exact of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, over they doe of themſelves; they will not allow them common, and humane infirmities: Their brethren
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59698:25"/>muſt live like Angels, themſelves like Divels; and yet be counted honeſt men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What <hi>inequality,</hi> if not iniquity is this in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? What partiality in judging? They can allow men of their owne confederacie, many groſſe, not infirmities, but crimes: Some drunkards, ſome whore-maſters, and what not? yet they heare, honeſt men, good neighbours, onely they have their infirmities: But if a profeſſour of more godlineſſe ſlip, and catch a fall (as who lives, and ſins not) his infirmities are made crimes; and himſelfe proclaim'd an hypocrite. Had theſe men lived in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> time, and ſeen his grievous falls, hee ſhould have heard, Hypocrite, and Counterfeit; and this is your holy <hi>David, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo he did from ſome, no doubt: <hi>The drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards made ſongs of him,</hi> perhaps for thoſe or the like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But what <hi>uncharitableneſſe</hi> is this, to condemne all for one? There was a <hi>Cham</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> family, an <hi>Iſmael</hi> in <hi>Abrahams,</hi> an <hi>Abſolom</hi> in <hi>Davids,</hi> a <hi>Judas</hi> in Chriſts; ſhall any be ſo raſh to ſay, They were all ſuch? A groſſe falſhood; all are not ſuch: There are many (bleſſed bee the grace of God) that ſhine as <hi>lights,</hi> in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe generation. Many, whom the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himſelfe (except but common infirmities) cannot accuſe juſtly of any <hi>ſcandalous</hi> ſin.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What <hi>hypocriſie</hi> is this, to lay the faults of profeſſours upon Religion; yea, that Religion which themſelves profeſſe, at leaſt in ſhew? For <hi>Papiſts</hi> to cenſure thus of our Religion were ſomewhat tolerable; but for <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> thus to flie in the face of their owne Religion, what heart can heare with patience? They know, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion allowes or teaches no ſuch thing: <hi>The grace of God, that brings ſalvation,</hi> teaches us to deny <hi>ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, &amp;c.</hi> The commandement is holy, and juſt, and good; though in the beſt profeſſion ſome have their infirmities, and ſome indeed be hypocrites: And the truth is, this man that thus ſtrikes at the head or heart of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59698:26"/>Religion, through the ſides of ſome weake profeſſours, diſcovers his owne hypocriſie: For if he did not hate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (in the power of it) he could not thus inſult and rejoyce in the ſhame of that, which yet he would ſeem to honour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, another ſort are thoſe, who take occaſion from mens ſinnes, to <hi>inſult</hi> over them, to <hi>ſcorne</hi> and deſpiſe them, as here the Phariſee did; <hi>God, I thanke thee, I am not as other men, &amp;c.</hi> Its ſtrange to ſee how ſuperciliouſly ſome (perhaps more civilly honeſt men) doe carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards thoſe, who are more ſcandalouſly ſinfull, whether preſumptuouſly, or by infirmity. How do they entertaine high thoughts of themſelves, and their owne goodneſſe, in compariſon of thoſe? How highly they over-looke them? how bigge they ſpeak? how ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? how reproachfull? like this Phariſee here, <hi>This Publican,</hi> and thoſe others elſewhere; <hi>This people that knowes not the Law, are curſed:</hi> Or thoſe their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of old, <hi>Stand farther off, I am more holy then thou: I thanke God, I am not as other men are, &amp;c.</hi> To let out this ſwelling impoſtumated <hi>pride,</hi> I would propound theſe few conſiderations:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This is no great matter to boaſt of; an hypocrite, an heathen, a reprobate may be no extortioner, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, no adulterer: Many ſuch have been among the Gentiles, as civilly honeſt as they.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This is but a negative kind of goodneſſe, that is not to be better, but leſſe ill then others; which is indeed a poſitive kind of illneſſe, though in a lower degree: but to be leſſe ill, is not to be good; unleſſe to be ill, be to be good. And if he may be accounted good who is leſſe ill, there are ſcarce any bad upon earth; none almoſt ſo bad, but he may find worſe, if not here, yet in hell: <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> might prove to be good and honeſt men, for no doubt there were ſome worſe then they. Nay, I dare be bold to ſay, there are many better then this negative man in hell; there are ſome, who not only were no adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59698:26"/>extortioners, &amp;c. but chaſte, and charitable, and have done many good workes in appearance: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is but a poore matter to boaſt of; not ſo bad as others on earth, not ſo deep as others in hell.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This may come from reſtraining, not from ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace; and what is a man the better for that? A Lion in a chaine cannot range and devoure, as he would doe: The Divell himſelfe, that roaring Lion, is held in the chaine of Gods Almighty providence, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe the miſchiefe which hee would. Their nature is never the better for that: Thou art no extortioner, no adulterer; perhaps thou wouldſt, but durſt not, but couldſt not: Is this a thing to boaſt of?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But grant all this, yet who may they thank for it? not themſelves, not their owne better nature, or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; but God that hath chained up their corruption, and let looſe others to their owne hearts luſts. If others be ſo and ſo, they are to be pittied, not ſcorned: If any man be not ſo, he ought to be the more thankfull, not proud and ſcornfull; Who made him to differ? What hath he, that he hath not received? Why then doth he boaſt, as if he had not received it?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Yet ſee the hypocriſie of men diſcovered: I thank God, ſayes one, I am not an extortioner, not an adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, &amp;c. What great matter is this? All men are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, or adulterers: Some have another luſt predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant their <hi>veine</hi> lies another way: One man hates adultery, but loves drunkenneſſe: Another hates prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, but loves covetouſneſſe: Say then, thou proud Phariſee, I am no ſlanderer, or detracter from other mens credit; I am not proud: but that thou canſt not ſay: Thou art not like the Publican indeed, for he, though a ſinner, was humble; thou art a ſinner, and proud. Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men have ſeverall waies to ſpend and vent their luſt; all are damnable: Boaſt not then, I am no adulterer, when thou art a blaſphemer, or covetous, or proud, &amp;c. that is palpable hypocriſie.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:59698:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> A fourth ſort of hypocrites are ſuch, as delight, and are glad to ſee or heare, or perhaps to tell and blaze a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad the faults and falls of others. Some have <hi>itching eyes,</hi> deſirous to ſee or know: Some have <hi>itching eares,</hi> tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled and contented to heare the worſt reports, eſpecially of profeſſours; and <hi>itching tongues,</hi> that pleaſe themſelves in raking in the infirmities of other men: <hi>Tell-tales,</hi> that like Pedlars goe up and downe from houſe to houſe, and open their packs at every doore: Did you not heare what ſuch a one hath done? I am ſorry to ſpeake it, I pray tell nobody; when ſecretly he is glad, and deſirous all ſhould know it. Such a fellow was that curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> who could not ſatisfie his wickedneſſe to ſee, but muſt needs run and tell his brethren of his fathers nakedneſſe; whereas his brothers took no delight to ſee it; therefore they went backward, and threw their garments over it, to ſhew how diſpleaſingly they heard ſo vile a report of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.8.</note>Such an hypocrite was <hi>Doeg,</hi> who (forſooth) was <hi>detentus coram Jehova,</hi> detained before the Lord at Nob, whether with conſcience of the Sabbath, or ſome vow, it matters not; yet in the next Chapter, turnes Informer againſt <hi>David: I ſaw the ſonne of Iſſai coming to Nob, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> This he did, either to flatter, and humour, and curry fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with <hi>Saul;</hi> or to vent his ſecret ſpleen and malice againſt <hi>David,</hi> whoſe vertues were more eminent, and whoſe fame eclipſed his. But <hi>David</hi> brands him for a ſtarke hypocrite for his labour, and for a lying fellow, though he ſpake but the truth: <hi>Why boasteſt thou thy ſelfe in miſchiefe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.1.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>O thou mighty man? Thy tongue deviſeth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, like a ſharp raſour, working deceitfully: Thou loveſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill more then good</hi> (for all thy faire pretences of devotion) <hi>and lying rather then to ſpeake righteouſneſſe: Thou loveſt all devouring words, O thou deceitfull tongue.</hi> Why (might ſome man ſay) <hi>Doeg</hi> told nothing but the truth; why then is he thus complained on? Why? becauſe he ſpake the truth with an ill mind, in an ill manner, boaſting and inſulting over <hi>Davids</hi> infirmity, as if he were glad of this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59698:27"/>advantage, to <hi>ingratiate</hi> himſelf with <hi>Saul,</hi> and to do <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> a miſchief: Such <hi>Doegs</hi> there are too many now, <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical mockers at feaſts</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> calls them) trencher-flies, who fall upon the ſores of thoſe that profeſſe godlineſſe; to pleaſe ſome, to whom they know ſuch newes will be welcome: men notwithſtanding that ſeeme ſometimes very pious and devout, holy with the holy: this ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, to heare or tell others infirmities, diſcovers them for hypocrites; and theſe are the fourth ſort.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Another ſort are ſuch as <hi>envie</hi> at others goodnes, or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit thence ariſing: <hi>Some preach Chriſt out of envie,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle; and how glad were they to ſpie out the failings of thoſe that preached in ſincerity? Now this is certaine, He that is envious at others goodneſſe, will rejoyce, or be much pleaſed with his badneſſe. <hi>Paul</hi> was of another diſpoſition; <hi>Notwithſtanding, whether in pretence, or in truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1.18.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt is preached, and I therein doe rejoyce, and will rejoyce.</hi> Good men deſire all men were as good, yea better then themſelves; this they pray for: <hi>I would to God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) that all the Lords people could propheſie. I would to God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Agrippa) not onely thou, but even all that heare mee this day, were altogether ſuch as I am.</hi> To conclude, ſee you a man proud, vain-glorious, and conſequently envious? certainly, that man cannot but take delight in ſeeing and hearing others badneſſe: Envie feeds it ſelfe upon others evills; it is as pleaſant to him, as his meat and drinke. But to allay this curſed diſpoſition in them all, I propound but theſe three things to their conſideration:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This argues, that they are deſtitute of all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>charity,</hi> and love of their brethren; <hi>Love envieth not; love rejoyceth not iniquity,</hi> its owne or others: That man that ſhould ſee his very enemy fall, and break a legge or an arme, &amp;c. and rejoyce at it, were a beaſt, and no man. But he that ſhall ſee his brother fall into ſin, and break not a legge or arme, but the neck of his ſoule, if I may ſo ſay, and make himſelfe and others ſport with it, hath put off man, and put on Divell. The Divell indeed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59698:28"/>rejoyces at the falls of men: As there is joy in heaven for one ſinner that repents; ſo, no doubt, there is joy in hell for one penitent that relapſeth. I may allude to Saint <hi>James:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 3.14, 15.</note> 
                     <hi>If you have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts</hi> (which will certainly cauſe rejoycing at others e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill) <hi>glory not, and lye not againſt the truth.</hi> This wiſdome (or folly rather) deſcendeth not from above, but is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſuall, <hi>divelliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. As they have no love of their brethren, ſo nor any love of God (what ever they may pretend) that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in his diſhonour. Nothing more diſhonours God, then the ſcandalous lives of profeſſours; and canſt thou rejoyce in that which grieves and diſhonours him? Can any good childe ſport himſelfe in his fathers diſgrace? I will ſay to thee, as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer, <hi>Thou childe of the Divell, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe;</hi> what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pretence or profeſſion thou makeſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This is enough to diſcover ſuch for hypocrites; what ſhew of love to Religion ſoever they make, they doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hate it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> God himſelfe challenges ſuch, <hi>To the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>what haſt thou to doe to preach my Law, and to take my Covenant in thy mouth; whereas thou hateſt to be reformed?</hi> Wherein (might he ſay) doe I hate to be reformed? Marke what followes; <hi>Thou ſateſt</hi> (in the ſeat of ſcorners) <hi>and ſpakeſt againſt thy brother, and haſt ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thine owne mothers ſonne:</hi> Thou takeſt delight to be ſpeaking of thy brother, things either true or falſe, it matters not; and this concludes thee for an hypocrite. No ſound member of the body can delight it ſelfe in the diſeaſe or diſhonour of a fellow-member: <hi>If one member ſuffer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.26.</note> 
                     <hi>all the members ſuffer with it: if one member be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all the members rejoyce with it.</hi> Let theſe things bee conſidered; and ſo we proceed to the ſecond uſe.</p>
                  <p>And that is for <hi>direction,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Directions, what uſe to make of others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alls.</note> how to ſtand affected at others badneſſe, and what uſes we ought to make, if (at leaſt) we will approve our hearts either to God or men, or our ſelves to be ſincere. To inſult and be glad at others bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59698:28"/>that they are worſe then we, is a ſigne of a naughty and hypocriticall heart: What then is to be done in ſuch a caſe? We cannot but ſee daily the out-flyings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens corruptions, into many foule and ſcandalous ſinnes; and what uſe worldly men and hypocrites make thereof, to triumph in their falls, we have heard already; which being conſidered, let us ſee what uſe we ought to make: Wee will reduce all to theſe foure heads; 1. To humble us, 2. to make us thankfull, 3. to make us, pitifull and mournfull, 4. to make us watchfull.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt uſe we ſhould make, is to <hi>humble</hi> us,<note place="margin">1. Humility.</note> conſideration of our common frailty. It was a Heathen mans advice, When thou beholdeſt other mens infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, reflect upon thine owne heart, and aske thy ſelfe, <hi>Numnam ego talis?</hi> Did I never commit the ſame, or the like as bad? Yea, the Apoſtle inferres all meekneſſe to be uſed to all men, upon this very ground:<note place="margin">Tit. 3.3</note> 
                     <hi>For wee our ſelves were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, ſerving divers luſts, &amp;c.</hi> Or, if not ſo, yet aske once more, May I not be ſo? May I not fall as foule as he? Have I not the ſame nature? the ſame corruption? even this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Apoſtle alſo urges;<note place="margin">Galat. 6.1.</note> 
                     <hi>If any man be overtaken a ſlip or infirmity, you that are ſpirituall, reſtore him with the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſidering thy ſelfe, leſt thou alſo be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> That ſinne (as well as miſery) may befall every man, that doth befall any man: Yea, wee ſhould be ſo farre from inſulting and rejoycing at it, that we ſhould trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at their fall, &amp; at the juſtice of God in ſuffering it. To be given over to a mans owne hearts luſts, is one of the moſt fearfull judgements that can befall a man:<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.12.</note> 
                     <hi>So I gave them up to their owne hearts luſts, and let them follow their own imaginations;</hi> as if hee knew not how to puniſh them worſe. To puniſh a man with <hi>ſinning,</hi> is the worſt part of puniſhment. Now all Gods judgements ought to be trembled at, much more the greateſt. If we ſee a man ſuddenly ſtruck dead by the peſtilence, or other diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Acts 5.11.</note> wee are amazed, and tremble at it; how much more
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59698:29"/>ought we to doe ſo, when we ſee a man ſtruck downe with ſinne? And that the rather, when we conſider, that it might have been our caſe, having the ſame nature, the ſame deſert in both? we have as great ſinnes to provoke God, to let our corruptions looſe, to ſhame both our ſelves and our profeſſion:<note place="margin">Rom. 11.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold the goodneſſe and ſeverity of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle in a like caſe: Goodneſſe to thee, ſeverity to them that fall; mercy to thee, juſtice to them: and when thou beholdeſt, be humble and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Tremble, I ſay, at his ſeverity to them, and his goodneſſe to thee, if thou continue in his goodneſſe; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (marke what followes) <hi>even thou alſo ſhalt be cut off:</hi> ſhalt be let looſe, and fall as foule as they. <hi>Thou wilt ſay then</hi> (to allude to the Apoſtle) <hi>They are fallen, but I ſtand upright:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 19</note> Well, they are fallen by unbeliefe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, or ſome other ſinne, by the juſtice, and juſt judgement of God; <hi>and thou ſtandeſt by faith</hi> (if ſo bee thou haſt faith) <hi>be not high-minded, but feare.</hi> If God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not them, take heed leſt he ſpare not thee. And that is the firſt uſe to be made of others falls.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond is for <hi>thankfulneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> that wee are not ſo bad. The Phariſee ſuppoſed right, had he but proceeded right; had the manner been ſutable to the matter, no man could have ſpoken better. It is worth abundance of thankes, that wee are not as other men are, &amp;c. as hath been largely proved in the former point: we will but borrow the remembrance of the chiefe heads, to quicken the exhortations, and then proceed to another. There is great reaſon we ſhould ſay (with a more humble heart then the Phariſee) <hi>God, I thanke thee, that I am not as other men are, not an extortioner, &amp;c.</hi> I know not whether is the greater mercy,<note place="margin">Omnia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata ſic haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da tanquam dimittantur, à quibus Deus cuſtodit ne committan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </note> to <hi>forgive</hi> a ſinne, when it is committed: or to <hi>prevent</hi> a ſinne from being committed: I will not diſpute the caſe; but propound the reaſons of our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If we conſider the <hi>ſpawne</hi> and ſeed of corruption, which lies bedded in our hearts, waiting but opportunity
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59698:29"/>to breake out into the ſame enormities; there is not the vileſt ſinne that ever was committed, but we might and ſhould commit, did not God in much mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine us. We admire and wonder at others badneſſe; we need not, if we conſider the root from whence it proceeds: but rather wonder we are not as bad, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Gods goodneſſe wee are not. It is, wee ſaid even now, one of the greateſt judgements of God, to let cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption looſe upon a man, and to deliver him into the power thereof. It is conſequently one of the greateſt mercies, to have it chained up from breaking out: and therefore ſay humbly, <hi>God, I thanke thee, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In regard of the <hi>iſſues</hi> and conſequents of ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which are manifold and grievous miſeries, which our eyes have ſeen overtake men for their ſinnes which they have committed: A wounded ſpirit, broken bones, as <hi>David</hi> calls them; ſorrow, ſickneſſe, poverty, ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſhame to themſelves, friends, profeſſion, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion it ſelfe; death temporall, yea, and perhaps eternall: from all which we are freed, by being kept from their ſinnes. Conſider but what they would give to be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent againe, if poſſible; and thinke what a mercy it is, to be kept from their ſinne, and their miſery: and then goe and bleſſe God, and ſay, <hi>God, I thanke thee, &amp;c.</hi> wee cannot but ſtand amazed, that many, and they in our opinion and their owne, godly, learned, wiſe, &amp;c. have fallen into ſo many great and foule ſinnes, to their owne ſhame, ſorrow, miſery, and the ſcandall of religion, &amp;c. Why are not we fallen into the ſame pit? Are we bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they? Nothing at all: It is the grace of God that makes this difference between us: Bleſſed be God, and his grace for his mercy. Oh then, doe not inſult o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men wounded, and fallen at our feet, doe not rejoyce at them, but, with all humble thankfulneſſe, adore and bleſſe that grace that hath preſerved us from falling.</p>
                  <p>But it is not enough not to rejoyce or triumph at the falls of others;<note place="margin">3. Compaſsion or mourning.</note> it is alſo a duty required to <hi>mourne</hi> with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59698:30"/>them, and for them: This I am ſure, was the practiſe of holy men heretofore;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> ſo did <hi>David, I was grieved to ſee the tranſgreſſours: Mine eyes guſht out with rivers of teares, becauſe men keep not thy Law.</hi> So did Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in a caſe of a ſcandalous ſinne,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.4.</note> by the inceſtuous perſon: <hi>Out of much affliction and anguish of heart, I wrote unto you with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teares:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Some walke</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of whom I have told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and now tell you weeping, &amp;c.</hi> And there is very good reaſon for it: for</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Otherwiſe thou art like to fall into the ſame, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſinne as bad, and as ſcandalous. Into the ſame, firſt: For nothing better to preſerve a man from the infection of other mens ſinnes, then to be grieved and mourne for them: This kept juſt <hi>Lot</hi> from the hurt of Sodoms ſins, living amongſt them,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> that <hi>he vexed his righteous ſoule, in beholding their uncleane converſation.</hi> Upon this ground the Apoſtle told his Corinthians, that <hi>a little leaven would lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the whole lump;</hi> even infect them, that had not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for the ſinne committed by the inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Or if thou eſcapeſt the ſame, it is juſt with God, to let thee fall into <hi>another</hi> ſinne as bad and infamous; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou doeſt not compaſſionate and mourne for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinnes, much more, if thou in the leaſt manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceſt at his fall: The unmercifulneſſe and ſcorne of men is ſometimes thus requited. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes of an enemy,<note place="margin">Pro. 24.17.</note> may very well be applyed to this purpoſe: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce not at thine enemy when he falleth</hi> (into miſery, or ſin) <hi>neither let thine heart be glad, when he ſtumbleth; leſt the Lord ſee it, and it diſpleaſe him, and hee turne his hand from him, upon thee;</hi> and ſuffer thee to fall into the like, or as bad a ſinne, to find as little mercy and compaſſion, or as much ſcorne and contempt, as thou haſt ſhewed to thy brother. I doubt not, but this hath overtaken many of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; they have been let goe, to fall: becauſe they have not pittied and mourned with others that have fallen by them. God cannot endure that men, ſubject to the like infirmities, ſhould be proud and inſult, or be mercileſſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59698:30"/>and pittileſſe towards others; and therefore oftentimes payes them in their owne coine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But if not ſo, yet thou ſhalt be <hi>guilty</hi> of others ſins, for which thou haſt not mourned; much more, if rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at it. The Apoſtle charges his Corinthians for a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fault in this kind: one,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.2.</note> that they did not <hi>mourne</hi> for that ſcandalous ſinne; another, that they were <hi>puffed</hi> up, ſwelled againſt him, inſulted over him: and this made them double guilty of his ſinne. Contrarily, when they had mourned for that ſinne, he gives them their acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; <hi>Behold this very thing, that ye have been godly ſorry,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11.</note> what Apologie it hath wrought for you: ye have ſhewed your ſelves free in this matter. It may ſeem a paradox, but is a truth; A man is guilty of all thoſe ſinnes of the times he doth not <hi>mourne</hi> for: but if he ſhall adde, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at them, or take pleaſure in them that doe them, as the Phariſee did, he ſhall be double, yea treble guilty of them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And if guilty of the ſinne, lyable to the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Be not partakers of her ſinne, leſt yee bee partakers of her judgements,</hi> is a caution preſcribed ſpecially in the caſe of Babylon; but may extend to any nation, or particular perſons ſinne. This was once proved on the contrary, in a common deſtruction, the mourners onely were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved:<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Goe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſet a marke upon the fore-heads of all thoſe that mourne for all the abominations committed in the city;</hi> and then ſmite the reſt, and ſpare none: Let this be conſidered.</p>
                  <p>The laſt uſe that we are to make upon the view and conſideration of others falls and infirmities,<note place="margin">4. Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</note> is to be more <hi>watchfull</hi> over our owne hearts and waies. The Apoſtle makes the concluſion for us:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Let him therefore that thinkes he ſtands, take heed leſt hee fall:</hi> Not onely their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but their ſinnes are written for our example, that we ſinne not as they did. They are written for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition; they murmured, they committed Idolatry, they fell into fornication, they tempted; we are made of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59698:31"/>the ſame metall, ſubject to the ſame infirmities: Let no man therefore inſult over their falls, upon conceit of his owne ſtrength; but <hi>let him that thinkes hee ſtands, take heed leſt hee fall.</hi> The like may be ſaid concerning thoſe, who fall into ſcandalous ſinnes in our own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: <hi>Conſider thy ſelfe, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi> This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation is very ſeaſonable, To walke <hi>circumſpectly,</hi> to walke <hi>exactly,</hi> eſpecially to thoſe, who make a more then ordinary profeſſion of Religion, conſidering</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Our owne frailty.</note> Our owne frailty, even the ſtrongeſt of us; wee are made of the ſame matter, have the ſeed of the ſame ſinnes in us: But when wee ſee men farre better then our ſelves ſo foulely overtaken, how ſhould we chuſe but tremble, and watch and pray againſt our owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes?<note place="margin">Neh. 13.26.</note> That place of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> is pertinent, <hi>Did not</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon <hi>King of Iſrael ſinne by theſe things? yet among many Nations was there no King like unto him, who was beloved of God: nevertheleſſe him did outlandiſh women cauſe to ſinne.</hi> Whence the Argument is ſtrongly enforced: Did <hi>Solomon?</hi> Did <hi>David?</hi> Did <hi>Peter</hi> ſo ſtumble, and fall ſo foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hainouſly? men of admirable wiſdome, ſtrength, and piety? who then may not feare to fall? If the <hi>Cedars</hi> of Lebanon were ſo ſhaken, ſo broken, how had the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer under-wood need to look to their ſtanding? If men of yeares and ſtrength ſlip and fall, how had children need to look to themſelves?</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. The iſſues of ſuch falls: for</note> Conſidering the iſſues ordinarily of the falls of thoſe that profeſſe godlineſſe, the ſinfull example of a wicked man doth much hurt, but nothing to that of a Profeſſour: For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. It hardens ſome wicked.</note> This more <hi>hardens</hi> ſome that are wicked in their courſes; Why the beſt men have their infirmities: nay, doe ſometimes as bad as we; <hi>Noah</hi> was drunken, <hi>David</hi> adulterous, &amp;c. and yet good men, and ſaved.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. It grieves the godly.</note> This more <hi>grieves</hi> thoſe that are good: Nothing wounds their ſoules more, then to ſee their fellow-bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren fall ſo foulely; <hi>Paul</hi> was grieved much for his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59698:31"/>the Jewes that were not, nor would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; but more, I beleeve, for that ſinne and ſcandall of the inceſtuous perſon, who was a Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This more <hi>diſgraces</hi> Religion,<note place="margin">3. It diſgraces Religion.</note> and conſequently keeps men off from being religious: The very rumour and ſlander of the Primitive Chriſtians, that they were inceſtuous, and adulterous, was a ſtrong engine of the Divell to keep many from being converted, eſpecially the civiller ſort of the Heathens: They could not love that Religion that allowed (as they were told and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved) ſuch monſtrous iniquities. And at this day, what keeps the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Jewes</hi> from being Chriſtians, but the wicked lives of many profeſſing Chriſtianity? Amongſt us Chriſtians, what withholds many <hi>Papiſts</hi> from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting, but the diſſolute lives of many Proteſtants? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> what keeps many, otherwiſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy honeſt, from being altogether Chriſtians, that is, truly godly, but the ſcandalous lives of ſome Profeſſors? That <hi>Indian,</hi> laboured by the Jeſuites to become a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, having asked, what became of the Spaniards when they dye, and of his owne fore-fathers; and being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the latter went to Hell, the former to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: replyed, that he would rather goe to Hell with his fore-fathers, then to Heaven with the Spaniards; and all, becauſe he ſaw thoſe barbarous cruelties committed upon his country-men by the Spaniards: <hi>It cannot bee</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>but offences will come; but woe to the man by whom they come:</hi> Woe to the world, becauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; woe to the takers; woe, yea twice woe to the givers: It were better that a mill-ſtone were hanged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their neckes, and they caſt into the Sea, then that they ſhould lay ſuch ſtumbling-blockes in the way of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: O therefore be watchfull, be circumſpect, walke wiſely towards them that are without; Give no offence to the Jew nor Gentile, nor to the Church of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laſtly, this more <hi>diſhonours</hi> not onely Religion,<note place="margin">4. It diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours God moſt.</note> but God himſelfe; when the Doctrine ſuffers, the Name of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59698:32"/>God ſuffers with it: It opens the mouthes of wicked men, even againſt God himſelfe. You may judge of Chriſt, by the lives of them that are called Chriſtians, ſaid <hi>Salvian</hi> of old. If Chriſt their Maſter were good, and his Doctrine good, theſe Chriſtians could not be ſo bad: Therefore the Apoſtle ſeriouſly adviſes people to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly religious,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>leſt the Word of God be blaſphemed,</hi> as a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or allower of ſuch things as are diſhoneſt. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.1.</note> 
                     <hi>that the Name of God, and his Doctrine be not blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:</hi> And to whom ſpeakes he this? Firſt, to wives, and they of the ordinary ſort too: Hee would have them be lovers of their husbands, lovers of their children, ſober, chaſte, keepers at home, obedient to their owne huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, that the <hi>Word of God be not blaſphemed, Tit. 2.5.</hi> Then to ſervants, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Let as many ſervants as are under the yoke, count their owne maſters worthy of all honour, that the Name and Doctrine of God be not blaſphemed.</hi> Alas (might ſome ſay) what credit or diſcredit can a poore woman, or a poore ſervant doe to Religion? Yes, much either way: Therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of wives, that he would have them vertuous and pious, <hi>that their husbands which beleeve not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>might be wonne by the converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wives.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.9.</note> that <hi>they ſhould be obedient to their owne maſters in all things, carefull to pleaſe, not anſwering againe, not purloyners; but ſhewing all good faithfulneſſe:</hi> To what end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? <hi>that they may adorne the Doctrine of God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in all things.</hi> The pooreſt and meaneſt Profeſſour that is, may doe much good or much hurt to Religion; and therefore my exhortation and adjuration to you all, that profeſſe Religion more then ordinarily, be you high or low, rich or poore, maſters or ſervants, is, that you walke <hi>circumſpectly,</hi> exactly, watchfully over your hearts and waies; and that the rather, becauſe there be many <hi>obſervers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.11.</note> as <hi>David</hi> calls his enemies, that watch for your <hi>halting,</hi> and will rejoyce to ſee even the meaneſt Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour ſlip or fall; and be ready to inſult over not onely
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59698:32"/>you, but your <hi>Religion,</hi> your fellow-brethren, yea in a manner, your God: I would have you therefore to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, not onely from groſſe evills,<note place="margin">1 Theſſal. 5.</note> but even <hi>from the very appearance of evill:</hi> Not onely to bee juſt, and faithfull, and ſober, and chaſte, and true in all your words, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, dealings, but to carry your ſelves ſo fairely, ſo openly, ſo clearly honeſt, and godly, that thoſe that watch for <hi>occaſions,</hi> may not have ſo much as the leaſt ground to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten a ſuſpition on; but may bee aſhamed, and (if God pleaſe) be converted, or convinced, when they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your blameleſſe converſation: Doe but thus walke, and you ſhall <hi>honour</hi> God, honour your fellow-brethren, (be you never ſo meane) honour Religion; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and God himſelfe ſhall honour you here, and in the end crown you with glory and immortality.<hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:33"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:33"/>
                  <p>VINDICIAE SPEI: SHEWING THE LAWFULNESSE of doing Good out of Hope of Reward.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the New Familie of Love the <hi>Antinomians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon, by <hi>D. C.</hi> Rector of Great Billing in Northampton-ſhire.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HEBR. 6.19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Which Hope we have as an Anchor of the ſoule, ſure and ſtedfaſt, and entring into that which is within the vaile.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Y.</hi> for <hi>Phil. Nevill,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gun in Ivie-lane. 1641.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:34"/>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59698:34"/>
                  <head>VINDICIAE SPEI. SHEWING The Lawfulneſſe of doing Good out of Hope of Reward.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2. John 8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>That we may receive a full Reward.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle having propounded an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, to <hi>Circumſpection,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Coherence.</note> in the former part of this verſe, <hi>(Looke to your ſelves)</hi> enforces it by a double argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, taken from a double danger, of a double loſſe; Loſſe of <hi>labour, (that we loſe not the things which wee have wrought,)</hi> and loſſe of <hi>reward; (but that we may receive a full reward.)</hi> Theſe words then, are the ſecond <hi>ground</hi> of enforcement, taken from the <hi>feare</hi> or danger of a ſecond loſſe; And there are in it conſiderable, theſe three particulars:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59698:35"/> 1.<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> The thing expected, <hi>A reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The degree of that reward, <hi>A full reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The expectation of that full reward; <hi>that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it;</hi> Looke to your ſelves, that we may receive it.</p>
                  <p>Of the two former we have already ſpoken;<note place="margin">Explication.</note> we are now to diſpatch the laſt: And the words carry this meaning with them; As if the Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid, <hi>We</hi> (or <hi>you,</hi> for the copies differ) <hi>doe expect to receive a reward, yea a full reward of our labour</hi> (and you of yours;) <hi>if you doe not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly looke to your ſelves, we, or you, or both, ſhall come ſhort of our hope; and loſe, if not all, yet at leaſt, ſome part of our reward; our reward ſhall not be ſo full as we expect;</hi> therefore I admoniſh and exhort you to look to your ſelves, leſt wee and you, loſing the things which wee (or you) have wrought, loſe alſo our reward : Looke to your ſelves that our <hi>expectation</hi> may not be fruſtrate; but that we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>receive,</hi> what we doe ſo earneſtly expect.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Concluſion</hi> hence reſulting will be this:<note place="margin">Obſervation. It is lawfull to doe Good in Hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: proved by</note> 
                     <hi>That it is lawfull</hi> (if not neceſſarie) <hi>for the beſt men, for their better incouragement in the ſervice of God, to have an eye upon the promiſed reward:</hi> Or thus, Hope of reward is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unlawfull, in doing of our dutie to God. This point, were it not for the ignorant clamors and preſumptuous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of ſome, need not any great confirmation, the thing is ſo apparant, both in Scripture and reaſon: But that we may give <hi>ſatiſfaction</hi> to them that doubt, or <hi>conviction</hi> to them that deny this truth; we will beſtow ſome paines in making it good: and that</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> By thoſe gracious <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God made unto us in the Scripture; which, what elſe can they import, but a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and lawfulneſſe at leaſt, to make uſe of them, to the beſt advancement of our performances? We inſtance in ſome: That to <hi>Abraham,</hi> is of this kind, to this purpoſe, <hi>Feare not, Abraham;</hi> Why? <hi>I am thy Shield, and thy exceeding great reward,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 15.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. And that's another, <hi>I am God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> 
                     <hi>walke before me, and be upright, Gen.</hi> 17.1. As if he ſhould ſay, Goe on, <hi>Abraham,</hi> in thy obedience to my
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59698:35"/>commands, feare nothing; and for thy encouragement take this my gracious promiſe, (which forget not to remember and make uſe of) I will be thy <hi>Shield</hi> to defend thee; and thy exceeding great <hi>reward,</hi> to recompence thee for all thy loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thou undergoeſt for my ſake. Looke often upon this promiſe, and be encouraged to goe on cheerefully. That is a moſt pregnant place,<hi>Deut.</hi> 28.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.1, &amp;c.</note> where <hi>Moſes</hi> layes downe a Catalogue of <hi>Bleſſings</hi> promiſed to obedience; <hi>If thou ſhalt hearken diligently unto the voice of the Lord thy God, &amp;c. Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the citie, and bleſſed in the field, &amp;c.</hi> To what purpoſe all this, if thoſe people might not, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their obedience, caſt an eye upon them? <hi>Moſes</hi> might have ſaved that labour both of repeating, and writing, and have barely propounded the will of God, and ſo have left them to chuſe whether they would obey, or no: As Kings proclaime their pleaſure, without any promiſe of reward, (or particular penaltie) at the ſubjects perill be it, if he refuſe to yeeld obedience. But leſt any ſhould ſay, This was indeed a courſe fit for the <hi>Paedagogie</hi> of the Law; Children muſt be drawne with ſweet allurements, as they with <hi>a land flowing with milke and honie;</hi> but the Goſpel gives more grace, and therefore, now, <hi>Love</hi> muſt ſupply the place, both of <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Feare.</hi> Take we ſome in the New Teſtament: Our bleſſed Saviour himſelfe, the only Lawgiver, not onely implicitely, in propounding bleſſedneſſe to thoſe particular vertues; but explicitely and plainly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.12.<note place="margin">Matth. 5.12.</note> He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes them to rejoyce and be exceeding glad, in perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon this very argument of our text;<note place="margin">Luc. 6.35.</note> 
                     <hi>For great is your reward in heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> So <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Love your enemies, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>your reward ſhall be great,</hi> &amp;c. Thus S. <hi>Paul</hi> 2. Cor. 7.1. <hi>Seeing therefore we have theſe promiſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> (to be the ſonnes and daughters of God, cap. 6. laſt) <hi>Let us,</hi> (upon the ſight of theſe Promiſes, and certaine expectation of their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance) <hi>cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> treads in the ſame ſteps: <hi>Wherfore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.14.</note> 
                     <hi>beloved, ſeeing ye looke for ſuch things</hi> (a new heaven, and a new earth, according to his promiſe) <hi>be diligent, that ye may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59698:36"/>be found, without ſpot and blameleſſe.</hi> I could be infinite in ſuch parallel places; which (I ſay againe) are all needleſſe arguments, if ſo be we may not make uſe of them, by exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci ſing of our <hi>Hope,</hi> to excite our diligence in thoſe injoyned dueties.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</note> By the <hi>Commands</hi> of Scriptures, founded upon thoſe promiſes, to exerciſe our <hi>Hope;</hi> How often, doe we heare it in the old Teſtament;<note place="margin">Pſal. 42 5. 130.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Hope in the Lord; Hope in his mercies &amp;c.</hi> Now what is <hi>hope,</hi> but the expectation of thoſe things which God hath promiſed? Can a man expect them, and not hope for them? Can a man hope for them, and not looke at them? Can he looke at them, hope for them, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them, and not be provoked to thoſe dueties to which they are promiſed? we have one pertinent place for all, and that in the new Teſtament;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.13.</note> it is S. <hi>Peters: Gird up the loynes of your minde</hi> (your fainting hearts) <hi>be ſober,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and hope to the end for the grace</hi> (i. the glory) <hi>that is to be brought unto you at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Hope to the end, or perfectly for that grace; and let that hope bee the <hi>Girdle,</hi> to gird up the loynes of your minde, &amp;c. Wee muſt <hi>hope;</hi> therefore wee may hope for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. The inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of</note> By the many <hi>Inſtances,</hi> even of men regenerate, that did looke at the reward promiſed: It is a generall deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good and holy men in Scriptures; by their <hi>Hope,</hi> and expectation of the Promiſes:<note place="margin">Luc. 2.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Old Simeon waited for the Conſolation of Iſrael. Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea looked for the Kingdome of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 15.43. Heb. 11.10. Phil. 3.20 Titus 2.13. 2 Pet. 3.14. Rom. 8.19</note> 
                     <hi>Abraham looked for a Citie. Wee looke for the Saviour, who ſhall change our vile bodie: Looking for the bleſſed hope, &amp;c. Seeing ye looke for ſuch things, &amp;c.</hi> Nay more; their hope is called, the earneſt <hi>expectation</hi> of the creature, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifies ſuch an intenſe <hi>expectation,</hi> as men expreſſe, when they looke for ſome lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for friend, and ſtand fixing their eyes, and thruſting them almoſt out of the holes of their heads; as if they would ſend their eyes to meet them, whom they think too long in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: Yea, if more may be, the Apoſtle hath another word,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59698:36"/>more emphaticall,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>They ſaw the Promiſes afarre off</hi> (by their faith) <hi>and embraced them, ſaluted them</hi> (ſo is the word) <hi>by their hope:</hi> They looked ſo earneſtly for them, as if they had ſent their hearts afore to <hi>ſalute</hi> them, which, yet they might not perfectly injoy; In particular:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man of God without exception, &amp; regenerate,<note place="margin">1. Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> (leſt any might object: We deny not the uſe of theſe to men unregenerate, to draw them on, till Love may come in place) This <hi>Moſes,</hi> (I ſay) as good as he was, was glad to ſtrengthen himſelfe from the <hi>Hope</hi> of Reward; <hi>He had an eye,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> (one eye at leaſt) <hi>to the recompence of Reward.</hi> If <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo good and holy a man as <hi>Moſes,</hi> had uſe, and it ſeemes, need of this helpe; how much more we, who (boaſt we what we will) I feare come farre ſhort of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s perfection. If any ſhall ſay (as ſome will) This was under, or before the Law; but the time of the Goſpel, is a time and ſtate of greater perfection: Take another,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of in this manner, <hi>You ſuffered with joy the ſpoyling of your goods:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Primitive Chriſtians. Heb. 10.34.</note> what ground of encouragement had they? did they if pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and meerely out of the ſtrength of their <hi>Love?</hi> heare on; <hi>Knowing that you have in heaven a better and more endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubſtance.</hi> A man will not throw away foule water, (we ſay) till he hath hope at leaſt, of faire. Nor would they (I ſuppoſe) ſo joyfully have parted with their earthly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, had they not had an expectation of an heavenly. But a weakeneſſe in them, to be checked, rather than allowed? marke what followes: he encourages them to it ſtill; ſtill to make uſe of their hope; <hi>Caſt not away therefore your confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which hath great recompence of reward.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 35</note> But leſt any ſhould ſay, Theſe were weaklings in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in <hi>Love,</hi> I adde.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Adam</hi> in innocencie: who certainly,<note place="margin">3. Adam.</note> being created after the Image of God, was perfect in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe; and if ever man did, hee might <hi>Love</hi> the Lord, with all his might, &amp;c. yet even <hi>Adam</hi> (it ſeemes) had need
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59698:37"/>of the ſame helpes; that we now have, the <hi>feare</hi> of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the one ſide; <hi>In the day thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die the death;</hi> and the <hi>Hope</hi> of reward on the other ſide, <hi>Doe this, and thou ſhalt live;</hi> which was the tenure of the old covenant, as we all know: If <hi>Adam,</hi> much more we. If any yet ſhall ſay, <hi>Adams</hi> was but a <hi>naturall</hi> love, but ours now is <hi>Supernaturall;</hi> I adde but one more:</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe: the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> both perfect and ſtrong every way, and therefore (wee may thinke) needed not ſuch helpes; as we doe: yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe (I doe not ſay, needed, I ſay) uſed this ſupportation of his <hi>Hope;</hi> and of reward ſet before him: The Apoſtle is plaine, <hi>Who, for the joy that was ſet before him endured the croſſe and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſhame.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 12, 2.</note> Would we thinke <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, ſo ſtrong as he was, would uſe this <hi>Helpe,</hi> if it were not lawfull to be uſed? Or ſhall we think our ſelves ſtronger then he, that we can goe without it? All which (to adde no more) are a ſufficient juſtification of the point propounded: But wee have beſide to confirme it</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Reaſons.</note> By <hi>Reaſons</hi> why it is lawfull, yea uſefull for us ſo to doe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Our <hi>Weakneſſe;</hi> which caſts us upon a neceſſitie of all the helpes, that can bee afforded us. It is true that S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Perfect love caſts out all feare; and hee that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth is not perfect in love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Joh. 4.18.</note> And it may peradventure be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as well to <hi>Hope,</hi> Perfect <hi>love</hi> caſts out all <hi>Hope;</hi> and he that hopeth is not perfect in love: I ſaid, peradventure it may be applyed to <hi>Hope;</hi> for I ſuppoſe, both <hi>Adam</hi> and Chriſt were perfect in love, and yet made uſe of their <hi>Hope:</hi> And we ſhall heare anon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that even in heaven, the Saints both now Have, and ever ſhall have uſe of their hope: but grant it for the preſent, <hi>Perfect love caſts out all Hope,</hi> and needs no helpe but her owne: Then I aſſume, But no man living is perfect in <hi>Love;</hi> and therefore no man living but hath need of his <hi>Hope,</hi> to be aſſiſtant to the imperfections of his love: <hi>He that hopeth</hi> (I grant for the preſent too) <hi>is not perfect in love;</hi> But I aſſume againe, Wee are not indeed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59698:37"/>perfect in <hi>love;</hi> and therefore we have need of <hi>hope:</hi> We know but in part, and therefore we beleeve but in part, and therefore hope but in part, and therefore love but in part; and therefore yeeld but a partiall and imperfect obedience, Our <hi>Obedience</hi> is meaſured by the degree, of our <hi>Love,</hi> our love by our <hi>Hope,</hi> our hope by our <hi>Faith,</hi> our Faith by our <hi>Knowledge;</hi> which being but in part, cauſes an imperfection in all the reſt: The truth is (however ſome preſume, upon their ſtrength) our weakneſſe is ſuch, that while, we carry about with us the old man, we muſt expect to goe ſtooping a little to the ground; and ſupport our ſelves with theſe two ſtaves, of <hi>Feare</hi> for the left hand, and <hi>Hope</hi> for the right hand, to ſtay up our <hi>Love</hi> from falling in the <hi>way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Our <hi>Humilitie</hi> requires as much:<note place="margin">2. Our Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</note> that ſeeing God himſelfe (who knowes us better than we our ſelves, and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties us as a father his children) allowes us theſe helpes; it is but fit, we ſhould with all thankfulneſſe make our uſe of them. When God had ſaid, <hi>It is not good for man to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I will make him an helper fit for him;</hi> had <hi>Adam,</hi> out of the confidence of his owne ſtrength, as being innocent, and free from all ſinfull concupiſcence, refuſed ſo gracious a tender, I ſuppoſe it would not have been well taken: The Lord himſelfe, of his owne good pleaſure, profered <hi>Ahaz</hi> a ſigne; <hi>Aske thee a ſigne, aske it in the depth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 7.11.&amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>or in the height above.</hi> And he returnes peremptorily, out of a fooliſh mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, <hi>I will not aske, neither will I tempt the Lord:</hi> But marke how roundly the Prophet takes him up, <hi>Heare ye now, O houſe of David, is it a ſmall thing for you to weary men, but will you wearie my God alſo?</hi> It is not <hi>Humilitie,</hi> but horrible pride and preſumption to refuſe and reject Gods offers (upon what pretences of ſtrength ſoever) and in a manner to ſcorne his helpes, which hee had never granted, but out of his infallible knowledge of our neceſſitie. It is not good (ſayes God) for <hi>Love</hi> to be alone, I will allow her <hi>Hope</hi> and (if need be,) <hi>Feare</hi> too, to be her helpers. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes then our modeſtie, in an humble ſenſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of our well-knowne weakeneſſe, to accept, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59698:38"/>make uſe of our ſo graciouſly allowed <hi>Helper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Application foure fold: For</note>And thus having ſufficiently confirmed the point, that it is lawfull, yea very uſefull for us to make uſe of our <hi>Hope,</hi> in eying the promiſed reward; Let us make it yet more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to our ſelves, by <hi>Application:</hi> It will yeeld us a</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Confutation of Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, by</note> 
                     <hi>Confutation,</hi> of the conceited perfection of the <hi>New Family of Love,</hi> if I may ſo call them; who no leſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly than preſumptuouſly, cry downe this doctrine, that I have thus ſtrongly confirmed; I meane the <hi>Antinomiſts,</hi> or, if you will, the <hi>Anomiſts</hi> of our time; who pretend, that they are ſo full of <hi>Love,</hi> that they ſcorne to be beholden either to <hi>Feare</hi> or <hi>Hope:</hi> They doe nothing, they, either for <hi>Feare</hi> of puniſhment, or <hi>Hope</hi> of reward; but all out of pure and meere <hi>Love</hi> of God: Neither doe they thinke a childe of God, a regenerate man, ought to doe any thing with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect either to the one or the other. For the fuller and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer conviction of this their errour, wee proceed in this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and manner, Firſt by way of <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of our former Truth to their errour: Secondly, by way of <hi>Propoſition</hi> of the many abſurdities that will follow upon that opinion: Thirdly, by way of <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the principall grounds of that their errour.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Oppoſing this Truth to their errour: For,</note> Whereas they ſay, a regenerate man ought to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of <hi>Hope</hi> of reward, but all out of <hi>Love,</hi> which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hath received warmth and ſtrength from that common received poſition of ſome Divines, <hi>That a child of God ſhould ſerve God, though there were neither heaven to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, nor hell to puniſh him:</hi> I anſwere;</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Love is not perfect.</note> It is one thing to ſay, what we ſhould doe; another what we doe, or can doe: The command indeed is, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, &amp;c.</hi> which if it were perfectly performed, might, perhaps, exclude the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe of <hi>Hope</hi> or <hi>Feare;</hi> but let mee ſee that man that ever did <hi>ſo love</hi> God; that durſt ſay, hee did ſo; except the old <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> and inſolent <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and theſe late upſtart <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiſts:</hi> What? are theſe men more perfect then <hi>Moſes?</hi> yet hee had an <hi>eye to the recompence of reward:</hi> Are they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59698:38"/>better than S. <hi>Peter?</hi> I doubt not but he loved <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as well and as ſtrongly as they; and preſumed upon the ſtrength of that <hi>Love,</hi> as much as they can doe, that <hi>though all men denyed him, yet would not hee:</hi> And yet you know how ſhamefully hee denyed his maſter, three times. But what? are they ſtronger than <hi>Adam</hi> in innocencie? His love, though ſupported both with <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Feare,</hi> failed him miſerably, as lamentable experience tels us: However, though they ſtick not, ſome of them with little leſſe than blaſphemie, to ſay, they are <hi>as perfect as Chriſt, Chriſted with Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> yet, I hope, they are not yet come to that height of pride, to thinke themſelves <hi>more perfect</hi> than Chriſt: <hi>who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſſe, &amp;c.</hi> what ſtrange preſumption is this? Mee thinkes I ſee them like little children, that have newly gotten their feete; who, proud and confident of their owne ſtrength, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the hand of the <hi>Nurſe;</hi> and will needs be going alone; till falls and broken faces teach them more wit. Certainly, this <hi>preſumption</hi> of theirs, preſages ſome fearefull fall, to the diſgrace of their <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and ſcandall of <hi>Religion;</hi> Let them but remember S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and I will ſay no more, but with Saint <hi>Paul, Let him that thinkes he ſtands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>take heed leſt he fall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. I adde, Their argument is infirme and inſufficient;<note place="margin">2. If it were, yet Hope uſefull.</note> A Chriſtian muſt doe all out of <hi>Love,</hi> therefore nothing out of <hi>Hope;</hi> or expectation of reward. This is to make the Graces of God to fall out one with another, which ſweetly do agree; A good thing may be done in <hi>Love</hi> of God, and yet in <hi>Hope</hi> of Reward too: Hope and Love are not contraries, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, like a paire of twinne-ſiſters, the daughters of one mother, <hi>Faith:</hi> or rather ſubordinate, and therefore may well concurre to the producing of the ſame effect; we may ſay, (as the Apoſtle of Faith) <hi>Hope</hi> works by <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> workes from <hi>Hope;</hi> as the Soule works by the hand, and the hand works from the Soule. And indeed, <hi>Love</hi> proceeds more immediately from <hi>Hope,</hi> then from <hi>Faith:</hi> Theſe three, (this is their order) <hi>Faith, Hope, Love;</hi> Faith is the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59698:39"/>ground of things hoped for, and ſo of Hope; and Hope is the ground of Love, as Love of Obedience: Why then ſhould <hi>Love</hi> thruſt out <hi>Hope,</hi> her mother, from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into her actions? It is <hi>in</hi> Love, but yet <hi>by</hi> Hope.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Hope ſhall never ceaſe: confirmed by reaſon.</note> I ſay yet further, <hi>(ex abundanti)</hi> whether wee ever ſhall be ſo perfect, as to doe all our ſervices to God, out of <hi>pure love,</hi> and nothing at all out of <hi>Hope;</hi> whether here on earth, or hereafter in heaven, is a diſputable queſtion. It ſeemes probable we ſhall not; I give my reaſons, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to the cenſure of the judicious; They are theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our <hi>Love</hi> of God, depends upon our knowledge of God, <hi>(ignoti nulla cupido)</hi> Our knowledge of God is onely of his <hi>back parts,</hi> as himſelfe cals them; which are ſuch qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> as have reſpect to us; <hi>The Lord is mercifull, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, long ſuffering, &amp;c.</hi> not ſuch as deſcribe him abſolutely in himſelfe, as he is <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> it ſelfe: His <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute is onely knowne to himſelfe, and therefore onely (ſo) loved by himſelfe: I conclude then, we cannot <hi>Love</hi> him but with reſpect to his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> to us, which is the object of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope;</hi> and ſo not without ſome mixture of <hi>Hope;</hi> that's the firſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Vide Aquin. <hi>22</hi> ae.q. <hi>19.</hi> a.<hi>6.</hi> c.</note> 
                     <hi>Selfe-love,</hi> (if moderate) is a naturall Impreſſe of God upon a mans Soule; and therefore (it ſeemes) to make a man love any thing for it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> without ſome reſpect to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> were to deſtroy mans nature: <hi>Praiſe the Lord, for he is good:</hi> why? <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Aquin.<hi>12.</hi> e.q. <hi>40.</hi> a. <hi>7.</hi> c. Ameſ. Theolog. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7. §. 2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Love</hi> proceeds from <hi>Hope,</hi> as the effect from the cauſe: For there we <hi>Love</hi> a thing, becauſe we <hi>hope</hi> to receive ſome good from that thing; we doe not (properly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly) <hi>hope</hi> in any thing becauſe wee <hi>love</hi> it, but onely by accident, in as much as we beleeve, we are beloved of it: Hence it will follow, that we cannot <hi>love</hi> God, but becauſe we firſt <hi>hope</hi> in him, as the Author of all our Good; and ſo <hi>hope</hi> will ever have Ingredience into our Love.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This is certaine, in the Judgement of the beſt Divines, that the Saints in heaven now have not loſt their <hi>hope;</hi> they live in hope of the Reſurrection of their bodies, <hi>My fleſh
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59698:39"/>ſhall reſt in hope, Pſal.</hi> 16.9. No,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.9.</note> nor after the reſurrection ever ſhall loſe their <hi>Hope;</hi> though there be ſome difference betweene our hope now, and then theirs and ours: For ours 1. ariſeth from <hi>Faith,</hi> theirs from <hi>ſight:</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Faith &amp; Hope how ſaid to ceaſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> Ours is with labour and contention, theirs without all difficultie. 3. Ours is imperfect, theirs perfect. That received opinion of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> ſhall ceaſe in heaven;<note place="margin">Vide Ameſ. Theolog. Pemble Vindiciae. p. <hi>198.</hi> &amp; <hi>199.</hi>
                     </note> is not to be underſtood of the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> or ſubſtance of thoſe graces; but of their imperfection , and manner of their uſe: <hi>Faith</hi> ſhall be perfected by Viſion, and <hi>Hope</hi> by Fruition: Wee ſhall then ſee, what now we beleeve; and enjoy, what now wee hope for. Yet ſhall there bee ſtill uſe both of Faith and Hope; in as much as there ſhall for ever be ſomething that wee ſhall never fully ſee; ſomething that we ſhall never totally and together enjoy: the Infinite eſſence and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, which no creature can comprehend: and the Eternitie of Happineſſe, which no creature can at once and together poſſeſſe; and therefore ſhall have uſe of <hi>Faith</hi> to beleeve the one, and <hi>Hope</hi> to expect the other; Thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions therefore of the Schooleman may be eaſily anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both concerning Faith and Hope;
<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>12.</hi> ae.q. <hi>67.</hi> a. <hi>3.</hi> c. Ibid. art. <hi>4.</hi> c.</note> 
                     <hi>That becauſe Faith is that whereby we beleeve what we doe not ſee; and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall ſee that which now we beleeve, therefore it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that Faith ſhould remaine.</hi> And againe, becauſe we hope for that which wee have not; and in heaven, have in poſſeſſion, that wee now hope for, therefore it is impoſſible hope ſhould remaine in heaven; For I aſſume, againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; But in heaven, there ſhall bee alwayes ſomething which wee ſhall not ſee; and ſomething we ſhall not enjoy, (without any derogation to our happineſſe) unleſſe hee will <hi>deifie</hi> the creature; therefore there ſhall be ſtill uſe of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> in heaven: And this may bee illuſtrated by the contrary <hi>Feare</hi> of the damned; which feare being (contrary to <hi>Hope</hi>) an expectation of evill to come, though the <hi>Feare</hi> that now wicked men have of hell ſhall ceaſe, when they once come in hell, feare being turned to preſent ſenſe and feeling; yet they ſhall be tormented with the <hi>feare</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59698:40"/>of the eternall ſucceſſion of their torments, which ſhall be one of the worſt pieces of their hell: So on the contrary ſide;<note place="margin">The Divels belive and tremble. Jam. 2.19. Pemble <hi>ubi ſupra, p.</hi> 197.</note> though <hi>Hope</hi> in the Godly, in regard of the complement of their <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> ſhall ceaſe, being turned into fruition; yet in regard of the eternitie of that fruition, their <hi>Hope</hi> ſhall be extended to eternitie: and this ſhall be no ſmall portion of their Happineſſe. His diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>feare</hi> of the damned, and <hi>hope</hi> of the bleſſed; that feare may better bee in the damned, than hope in the bleſſed, becauſe (forſooth) in the one there ſhall be a ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of puniſhments, and ſo there ſhall be a reſpect of futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition or time to come; and in the other, the glory ſhall be without ſucceſſion, after a certaine participation of eternity, in which there is neither time paſt, nor to come, but onely preſent: I ſay, this diſtinction is not true, (as I ſuppoſe) becauſe there is the ſame ſucceſſion of <hi>Happineſſe</hi> in heaven, as of torments in hell; in regard of the creatures, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finite, cannot infinitely at once enjoy their eternall happineſſe: God onely being infinite and onely eternally, at once and together enjoying his owne happineſſe: But enough of that: I now rejoyne; If there be, (as its proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) a continued exiſtence of <hi>Hope,</hi> and wee ſhall have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>Hope</hi> attending upon our <hi>Love,</hi> its as probable that <hi>Hope</hi> ſhall not be idle; but exerciſed often, if not continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, in viewing of its object, and that <hi>view</hi> cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite our love to all holy obedience, and that for ever: If not, then heare—</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Propoſing the many Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities of their opinion: For,</note> The many <hi>Abſurdities</hi> that will follow if that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be granted, that a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath no uſe of his <hi>hope</hi> to encourage himſelfe in the ſervice of God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. They make void the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> They <hi>vilifie,</hi> yea <hi>nullifie</hi> the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God, made to us in Scripture, at leaſt in regard of a regenerate man: For to what end are the <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to our obedience, if, for the better and more cheerefull performance of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, we may not, by the eye of hope, looke at them? To what purpoſe were <hi>Colours</hi> made, if the <hi>eye</hi> muſt be debarred the ſight of them? or muſicall ſounds, if the eare may not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59698:40"/>be permitted to heare them? &amp;c. Take away the uſe of the <hi>Senſe,</hi> and take away the object of that Senſe: Take away <hi>Hope,</hi> and away with all the <hi>Promiſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. They cannot evacuate <hi>Hope;</hi> but all other graces will vaniſh with it: The Graces of God are like a Chaine,<note place="margin">2. Deſtroy all Graces: as</note> draw but one linke, all the reſt will follow; <hi>Adde to your Faith vertue, &amp;c.</hi> Take away <hi>Hope,</hi> and take away all.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Joy;</hi> which (much of it) ariſes from Hope:<note place="margin">1. Joy. Rom. 12.12. and 5. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Rejoycing in hope. Rom.</hi> 12. 12. <hi>We rejoyce in hope of the glory of God, Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Lively hope— wherein ye rejoyce,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3, 6. Yea the greateſt and ſtrongeſt part of our <hi>Joy</hi> ſprings from <hi>Hope;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>That we might have ſtrong conſolation, who for a refuge,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>have laid hold on the hope ſet before us, Heb.</hi> 6.18.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Patience;</hi> which likewiſe is the daughter of <hi>Hope;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Patience . Rom. 8.25.</note> 
                     <hi>If we hope for the things we ſee not, we do with patience wait for them, Rom.</hi> 8.25. called therefore the <hi>Patience of Hope,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>For joy ſet before him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>endured the Croſſe, Heb.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelfe is likewiſe in danger; For though <hi>Faith</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Faith.</note> be the <hi>mother</hi> of Hope; yet Hope is the <hi>ſtaffe</hi> and ſtrength of <hi>Faith;</hi> and were it not for <hi>Hope,</hi> Faith it ſelfe would ſoone languiſh: <hi>Sanguis fidei, ſpes.</hi> Hope is as the blood of Faith:<note place="margin">Clem. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andr.</note> In the body, the blood is <hi>vehiculum animae;</hi> the charet of the ſoule, the life running in the blood; take away the blood, and you take away life: ſo take away <hi>Hope,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoc Ipſum quod Chriſtiani ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, fidei ac ſpei res eſt. Cypr. de Bono patient.</note> and <hi>Faith</hi> will ſoone expire: and therefore it is that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> are ſo often joyned together in Scripture; <hi>That your Faith and Hope might be in God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21 <hi>We, through the ſpirit, wait for the hope of righteouſneſſe, by faith, Gal.</hi> 5. 5. And we are ſaid to be <hi>ſaved by hope Rom.</hi> 8. 24 as well as by <hi>Faith.</hi> Take away Hope, and take away Faith.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Love</hi> alſo will not bee long after,<note place="margin">4. Love it ſelfe.</note> if you take away <hi>Hope;</hi> for <hi>Love</hi> it ſelfe (as I ſaid) proceeds from <hi>Hope,</hi> as well, and more immediately than from <hi>Faith:</hi> This is their order, in regard of cauſalitie and generation, as the Schoolman cals it; <hi>Faith, Hope, and Love. Faith</hi> produces Hope, and <hi>Hope</hi> produces Love; Becauſe we <hi>Hope</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59698:41"/>thoſe good things promiſed to, and beleeved by <hi>Faith;</hi> therefore we are moved to love him, that hath promiſed, and will performe them: <hi>Faith ſaies</hi> (ſaies devout <hi>Bernard) there are great and glorious things laid up for Gods Saints; Hope ſaies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Pſal. Qui habitat. 5.10.</note> 
                     <hi>they are reſerved for me; Love ſaies, I runne to them and embrace them: Faith beleeves them, Hope ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bern. de paſſ. Dom. c. <hi>43.</hi> Quantum quis credit, tantum ſperal; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſperat, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum amat.</note> 
                     <hi>and Love at laſt enjoyes them:</hi> And this is true, <hi>Looke how much a man beleeves, ſo much hee hopes; how much he hopes, ſo much the more hee loves. Love</hi> indeed proceeds both from <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope;</hi> but in a different conſideration: From <hi>Faith,</hi> as <hi>Faith</hi> apprehends the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as preſent; from <hi>Hope,</hi> as <hi>Hope</hi> expects the ſame mercy as future:
<note place="margin">A reſemblance of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> Or rather, we may ſee ſome reſemblance of the <hi>Trinitie</hi> in the proceeding of theſe three Theologicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues one from another: <hi>Hope</hi> iſſues from <hi>Faith</hi> alone, as the <hi>Sonne</hi> from the <hi>Father: Love</hi> proceeds from <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> as the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> from both the other perſons: Take away <hi>Hope</hi> then, and you deſtroy not onely this <hi>Trinity,</hi> theſe three, <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Charitie;</hi> but alſo the <hi>Unitie</hi> of proceſſion, and the very <hi>Eſſence</hi> of Love; as the joynt iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſue of <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Faith.</hi> In a word, <hi>Hope</hi> both breeds and perfects <hi>Love;</hi> we could not ſo love God for what hee hath done, but for the Hope of what hee will doe; ſo that I may apply that of the Apoſtle hither;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.19.</note> 
                     <hi>If we have Hope onely in this life, we were of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> Thoſe then that ſtand ſo much for <hi>Love,</hi> to the vilifying, yea nullifying of <hi>Hope,</hi> will in the end prove in themſelves a nullitie of <hi>Love.</hi> Little <hi>Hope</hi> little <hi>Love:</hi> No <hi>hope,</hi> no <hi>Love</hi> at all.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. All Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> Laſtly, (which they little thinke) all <hi>Chriſtian obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> is thus indangered, or at leaſt, a great part of it: For take away Hope, even hope of reward, and what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all good workes?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. Tom. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>175.</hi>
                     </note> Does not every reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture worke out of Hope? <hi>He that ploweth, ploweth in hope; and hee that threſheth, threſheth in hope:</hi> The <hi>Souldier</hi> warres in <hi>hope</hi> of victorie and ſpoile; the <hi>Mariner</hi> goes to ſea, in hope of gaine; and ſo of the reſt. If you think this hope hath no influence into our Chriſtian obedience; heare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59698:41"/>the Apoſtle; <hi>Hee that hath this hope; (to be like him) pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelfe as hee is pure:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Joh. 3.3.</note> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. And heare Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for both the parts of Sanctification; <hi>Seeing wee have ſuch Promiſes</hi> (to bee the ſonnes and daughters of God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> in the end of the former chap.) <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit;</hi> there's the firſt; <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting holineſſe in the feare of God;</hi> there, the ſecond: Hope therefore is a ſpeciall <hi>Principle</hi> of New <hi>Obedience,</hi> and that becauſe, 1. of the <hi>excellence</hi> and difficultie of the object,<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>12</hi> ae. q. <hi>40.</hi> a. <hi>8.0.</hi>
                     </note> which excite and ſharpen diligence, and 2. alſo in regard of the <hi>delectation</hi> and delight, the proper iſſue of Hope, which furthers and quickens operation; as he well obſerves: They then, that cry downe <hi>Hope,</hi> cry downe (by conſequence) all holineſſe and obedience. And now, I hope they will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they have brought the matter to a faire paſſe; that by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away one grace, have ſubverted all; <hi>Joy, Patience, Faith, Love,</hi> and all <hi>Obedience.</hi> But we have more to ſay yet.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The manifeſt <hi>injurie</hi> they doe to a Chriſtian Soule,<note place="margin">3. Deſpoile a Chriſtian, of</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving him of ſo neceſſarie a furniture, as <hi>Hope</hi> is: we will expreſſe it by a double <hi>Metaphor;</hi> of a Souldier, of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of a <hi>Souldier</hi> by land; Our life is a ſpirituall,<note place="margin">1. His Helmet.</note> and continued Warfare; There is a <hi>Panoplie,</hi> or whole-armour commanded to bee put on, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6. Amongſt the reſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17.</note> the <hi>Helmet of Salvation;</hi> which, what it is, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe tels us in another place, <hi>And for an Helmet, the Hope of Salvation.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.8.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.8.</note> They then that deny a Chriſtian this uſe of his hope, ſend him into the Field without his <hi>helmet,</hi> and ſo expoſe him to certaine danger.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of a <hi>Mariner,</hi> by ſea,<note place="margin">2. The wind at ſea.</note> then Hope hath a double uſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a double <hi>Metaphor</hi> in Scripture:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of the <hi>Wind, Heb.</hi> 6.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.11.</note> the full gale (ſo the word imports) or full aſſurance of hope. If the Chriſtian Soule be a <hi>Ship</hi> (ſailing in the ſea of this world) Faith may repreſent the <hi>Pilote,</hi> and Love the <hi>Saile;</hi> but Hope is the <hi>Wind,</hi> that muſt fill that Saile: Let the <hi>Pilote</hi> be never ſo confident, the <hi>Saile</hi> ſpread to the utmoſt, yet if it want a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59698:42"/>good gale of <hi>Winde,</hi> the ſhip lies becalmed; and her courſe is ever quicker or ſlower, as the <hi>wind</hi> riſes or fals: A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian on earth without Hope, is a Ship at Sea without winde.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">His Anchor. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 6.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chryſ ad Theod. Lapſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p. <hi>2.</hi> Tom. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>61.</hi>
                     </note> Of an <hi>Anchor:</hi> Heb. 6.19. <hi>which hope wee have as an Anchor of the ſoule, ſure and ſtedfaſt, &amp;c.</hi> A Ship may ſometimes have too much, or a contrarie <hi>Winde;</hi> and then ſhee hath need of an <hi>Anchor</hi> to fixe her, from being carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, eſpecially when ſhee drawes nigh her deſired <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Let <hi>Faith</hi> be the <hi>Ship,</hi> if you will, (and wee heare of ſome <hi>that make Shipwrack of Faith</hi>) Let <hi>Love</hi> bee the <hi>Merchandize,</hi> or paſſenger, to bee conveyed to heaven (when Faith and Hope, in a ſort, ceaſe, and ſtay behinde) yet Hope is the <hi>Anchor,</hi> that fixes the <hi>Ship</hi> from being toſſed to and fro, and carryed away with every <hi>winde of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> or wave of temptation, till <hi>Love</hi> the paſſenger, or merchandize be landed in the <hi>haven:</hi> As the <hi>Ship</hi> with all her tacklings and the <hi>Anchor,</hi> lye ſtill at Sea, but the paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and commodities are tranſported on Land: They then that deny this uſe of Hope, expoſe the Soule to certaine dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; either to be becalmed for want of <hi>Winde;</hi> or to bee carryed away, for want of an <hi>Anchor:</hi> If this be not enough, heare all:</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Incurre harſh cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note> The harſhneſſe of the <hi>Cenſure</hi> they are like to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe by this opinion: For if there bee no ſuch uſe of Hope, then marke,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either they are not yet converted, but in the ſtate of Nature ſtill; as being ſuch as the Apoſtle ſayes the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were, <hi>without hope, Epheſ</hi> 2.12. before their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or elſe, that they have loſt their hope, after once they had it,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3.</note>in Converſion; which cannot be, ſeeing a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man is <hi>begotten againe to a lively hope.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or elſe, (which ſome doe not ſticke to affirme) that we have alreadie all wee <hi>hope</hi> for that is, all alreadie <hi>glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied:</hi> For if wee may not hope for any more, it is, as if there were no more to bee hoped for: And this is it, which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59698:42"/>ſome both ſenſeleſly and ridicuouſly have affirmed (and well they may, upon their former opinion) <hi>that our glory in heaven ſhall be no other, no more,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Burtons</hi> Goſpel and Law reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led pag. 35. Rom. 5. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>than what we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but only in our ſenſe and apprehenſion;</hi> Contrary to the plaine text of the Apoſtle, <hi>We rejoyce in hope of the glory of God</hi> Theſe, and many more perhaps, are the <hi>Abſurdities</hi> wherewith this <hi>Novell</hi> opinion is heavily preſſed; which we leave to their more ſerious conſideration: and deliver</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The grounds of this their <hi>errour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the grounds of their errour,</note> as farre as wee can conceive, and there are theſe two, the common <hi>mothers</hi> of moſt errours:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Pride,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pride.</note> and ſtrange preſumption of their owne perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and of the ſtrength of their own (ſuppoſed) <hi>Love;</hi> that they can, and doe <hi>love</hi> God ſo well, that they need not be beholden to any inferiour helps; contrary to the experience of all good hearts, in all times, who were glad, and thankfull for theſe ſupportations of the weakeneſſe of their imperfect Love.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Ignorance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Ignorance of three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</note> the fertile<note n="*" place="margin">Uterus igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantae. Tertull. Apol.</note> 
                     <hi>wombe</hi> of all errours and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies whatſoever; However theſe men thinke themſelves wiſe, and able enough to teach their teachers, yet this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on manifeſts a manifold <hi>ignorance.</hi> We inſtance ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of the true diſtinction and uſe of Faith, Hope,<note place="margin">1. Of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and order of Faith, Hope and Charitie,</note> and Charitie; and that's the reaſon, that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> have devoured <hi>Hope</hi> betweene them: For let me aske them, Why doe they doe good workes? They will anſwere, Becauſe they <hi>Love</hi> God. I aske againe, Why doe they <hi>love</hi> God? Becauſe of their <hi>Faith;</hi> whereby they beleeve the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of God ſhewed toward them: All this is true, but not enough; for they ſhould have taken in Hope between Love and Faith, and ſaid, Wee <hi>love</hi> him, becauſe we <hi>hope</hi> in him; and <hi>hope</hi> in him, becauſe we beleeve in him: For this is the right order of theſe Graces. The good man is compared to a tree, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. the <hi>roote</hi> of this tree, is <hi>Faith;</hi> the <hi>ſtemme</hi> or bodie of it, is <hi>Hope;</hi> the <hi>branches</hi> of it, is <hi>Love;</hi> the <hi>fruit</hi> of it, are Good workes: Now it is true indeed, the <hi>fruit</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59698:43"/>growes immediately upon the <hi>branches, Good workes</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>Love;</hi> but the <hi>branches</hi> grow next upon the <hi>ſtemme,</hi> and not upon the root immediately, that is, <hi>Love</hi> proceeds from <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> from the roote of <hi>Faith:</hi> Let them learne this, and then they will not exclude Hope: but give it its due place.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. How a free gift and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward may ſtand together.</note> Of the poſſible <hi>Union</hi> of a <hi>Free-gift,</hi> with a <hi>Reward:</hi> For thus they ſeeme to reaſon; If all be of <hi>Free-gift,</hi> then is there no <hi>reward;</hi> is there no <hi>reward;</hi> if no reward, then no <hi>hope</hi> of reward. But this is their ignorance; Free gift and reward agree well enough together; The ſame thing may bee a <hi>Free gift,</hi> as not being merited by us; and a <hi>reward,</hi> as ſo promiſed by God; and then it is <hi>Juſt</hi> with him to performe his owne promiſe: The ignorance of this, is one cauſe of the popiſh <hi>Merit;</hi> Where there is a <hi>reward,</hi> there is <hi>Merit,</hi> ſay our <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts:</hi> and theſe men for feare of <hi>Merit</hi> have utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced all <hi>reward;</hi> whereas, wee ſay, There is a <hi>reward,</hi> where there is no <hi>Merit;</hi> and where there is a <hi>Free gift,</hi> there may be a <hi>reward</hi> notwithſtanding, freely promiſed, and faithfully performed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Of the right uſe of the Law.</note> Of the <hi>right uſe</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> to a regenerate man; and this is the <hi>Source</hi> and ſpring-head of all their erronious concluſions; For if there be no <hi>Law,</hi> it will follow; Then firſt, there is no uſe of promiſes; if no promiſes, then no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; if no reward, then no <hi>hope</hi> of Reward: Againe, if there be no <hi>Law,</hi> then are there no good workes; (for no worke is good without a command) if no good works, then no <hi>reward;</hi> and ſo no Hope: As on the contrarie, If there be no Law, then no ſinne; if no ſinne, then no puniſhment; if no puniſhment, then no <hi>Feare:</hi> So that this firſt <hi>Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie</hi> being granted, all the reſt will follow; which I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire they would ſeriouſly conſider. And ſo I leave them, and come to a ſecond uſe of</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Iustification of our practiſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Juſtification</hi> of our practiſe; I meane of us <hi>Miniſters</hi> who urge upon men, even the beſt men, the dueties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as with <hi>feare of puniſhments</hi> on the one ſide, ſo <hi>with Hope of Reward,</hi> on the other ſide: For which our method,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59698:43"/>we are by theſe <hi>Novellists,</hi> ſtiled Legall Preachers, &amp;c. But I would gladly be reſolved by any reaſonable man, why wee may not as well uſe the like arguments, as (I ſay not the prophets of old) <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? why may it not be as lawfull for me, to exhort men to the patient ſuffering of perſecution, and that with joy, as for our Saviour, with the ſame argument; <hi>For great is your reward in heaven?</hi> why may not I provoke men to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour of perfect Holineſſe, with remembrance of the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of God, the object of Hope, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did his <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Seeing we have theſe Promiſes, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Admiration,</hi> at the never enough admired <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of God, and our owne badneſſe: His <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</note> that will omit no meanes to doe us good; Commands,<note place="margin">1. Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> promiſes, threatnings; to worke upon our <hi>Love,</hi> by the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of his Commands; to perſwade our <hi>Hope</hi> by the <hi>Sweetneſſe</hi> of his Promiſes; and (if theſe will not prevaile) to <hi>ſcare</hi> us from our wicked courſes, by the <hi>terrours</hi> of his threatnings: He might (as Kings) command and expect our obedience; or puniſh our diſobedience; but no meanes ſhall be omitted to worke us unto Good. Our owne <hi>badneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Our owne Badneſſe.</note> that will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſcarce any of his meanes to doe our ſelves Good: Nor <hi>Commands,</hi> nor <hi>promiſes,</hi> nor <hi>threats</hi> can prevaile with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (too many of us) either to forſake evill, or doe good: What <hi>mettall</hi> are we made of, that no courſe can work with us! A King a mortal! man, commands, and wee obey; he threatens, and we quake; he promiſes and we runne: O the lamentable <hi>badneſſe</hi> of our hearts; O the admired <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of our God! &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Exhortation;</hi> that ſeeing we know our libertie,<note place="margin">4. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; where</note> wee learne to uſe it; to provoke our ſelves unto Good workes, by the <hi>Hope</hi> of the promiſed <hi>Reward:</hi> Bee not ſo ignorant, as not to know it; or ſo proud and preſumptuous, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſuch gracious Helpes, as God in mercy hath afforded us: We ſay to you, in the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> (and why may we not?) <hi>Cast not away your confidence</hi> (which is nothing but a confirmed <hi>Hope) which hath great recompence of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 35.</note>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:59698:44"/>
                     <hi>reward:</hi> And againe, <hi>Be not weary of well-doing, for in due ſeaſon you ſhall reape,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>if you faint not.</hi> And with S. <hi>Peter, Gird up the loynes of your minde, and hope to the end, &amp;c.</hi> Yet take ſome <hi>Cautions</hi> with you,
<note place="margin">1. The Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Good and bad, in uſe of Hope.</note> for your better directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the uſe of your <hi>Hope:</hi> For there is a <hi>Hope</hi> of reward lawfull, there is another unlawfull; Both good and bad are carryed with <hi>hope</hi> of Reward, but you ſhall obſerve a palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>difference,</hi> in theſe particulars:</p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. In the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hoped for.</note> A wicked man lookes at the <hi>preſent,</hi> not regarding the future; at a <hi>Temporall,</hi> not an <hi>eternall</hi> reward; Like that prodigall child, <hi>Father give mee the portion of goods, &amp;c. what profit,</hi> (preſent profit) <hi>is there in ſerving of God, ſay they, Mal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> What good? <hi>Corne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>and wine, and oyle,</hi> profit, pleaſure, honour; not ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or truſting to any thing hereafter: But the truly godly man lookes at things to come; and like a good child waites till the time appointed of his father; So S. <hi>Paul</hi> intimates the difference,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.18.</note> 
                     <hi>While wee looke not at the things that are ſeene</hi> (as worldly men doe) <hi>but at the things which are not ſeene; For the things which are ſeene are temporall, but the things which are not ſeen are eternall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. In the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation.</note> Wicked men looke at the reward, as a due <hi>debt,</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by their formall obedience; <hi>Give mee the portion of goods that belongs to me,</hi> ſaid hee; and therefore bargaine with God for it: The godly expect it, as a ſpeciall favour of promiſe; in all <hi>humility</hi> acknowledging themſelves leſſe than the leaſt of all Gods mercies; that's another.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. In the end.</note> Whereas there are three things in Scripture to bee eyed and obſerved, the <hi>command,</hi> the <hi>promiſe,</hi> and the <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> and it is not poſſible to looke upon them all at once with two eyes: A wicked man beſtowes both his eyes, one upon the <hi>threatning,</hi> the other upon the <hi>promiſe,</hi> but neither upon the <hi>command;</hi> A godly man, what ever he doe with one eye, to beſtow it either on the <hi>promiſes</hi> or threatnings; the other is ever fixed upon the <hi>Command:</hi> which diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is apparant by this; that where the <hi>Command</hi> comes without an expreſſe promiſe or threatning, a wicked man
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59698:44"/>will doe just nothing, neither forſake evill, nor doe good; Take a vaine-glorious man, tell him, God <hi>commands</hi> him to give almes; if you doe not tell him withall, You ſhall have <hi>applauſe</hi> and credite from men, if you doe it; or a curſe attending you, if you doe it not; hee lies like a Ship at Sea, <hi>becalm'd</hi> for want of wind; or a <hi>Mill,</hi> that moves no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the water runnes: yea that many times, neither <hi>Promiſes</hi> nor <hi>threats</hi> can make him ſtirre to performe an expreſſe <hi>command;</hi> which argues, that thoſe commands he performes, he doth it not out of reſpect of the command; but either out of hope of reward or <hi>feare</hi> of puniſhment: On the other ſide take a good man, tell him, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord;</hi> this is Gods will and command; though you ſay nothing of the promiſe or threatning; he is like the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turions</hi> ſervant, if he ſay, <hi>Goe, he goes, &amp;c.</hi> That's the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that <hi>David</hi> intimates, when hee ſayes unto God; <hi>I have an eye, or reſpect, to all thy commandements.</hi> As a good ſervant, that reſpects his Maſter; Let ſtrangers ſay, Goe, or Come, he ſtirres not, becauſe hee reſpects them not, though perhaps, they promiſe or threaten; but if his Maſter doe but <hi>winke</hi> with his eye, or <hi>nod</hi> with his head, intimating his pleaſure, hee preſently runnes. The Command of God is the <hi>wind</hi> that fils his Sailes; as that phraſe is elegantly uſed by the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>;<note place="margin">Phil. 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all the will of God;</hi> as a Saile with wind.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe wicked men will pretend <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a <hi>Command;</hi> there is yet another difference obſervable:<note place="margin">4. In the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> and that is, That where theſe two meere (as ſometime they doe) a <hi>Command,</hi> and a <hi>Promiſe;</hi> a wicked man doth it <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally</hi> out of the <hi>Hope</hi> of reward, and <hi>ſubordinates</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to his owne profit. Take but an inſtance or two: <hi>Balaam</hi> goes to <hi>Balaac,</hi> as hee was commanded, or rather permitted by God: but the Load-ſtone that begun this motion was that wages of iniquitie,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.15.</note> the Reward promiſed by <hi>Balaac.</hi> The like may be noted in <hi>Jehu,</hi> who drave furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the execution of Gods command (as he would ſeeme) upon <hi>Ahabs</hi> familie; and in pretence cryes, <hi>Come ſee the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59698:45"/>zeale, &amp;c.</hi> But the firſt Mover of all this fury (rather than zeale) was that meſſage of the Prophet, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I have annointed thee King over Iſrael.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. King. 9.6, 7.</note> The <hi>Kingdome</hi> was principally in his eye; and if he might have ſafely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed that, without any further danger, I doubt whether <hi>Jehoram,</hi> and <hi>Jezabell,</hi> and the reſt had dyed. With a <hi>Godly</hi> man it is quite contrary; where he hath an eye upon the <hi>Reward,</hi> he ſubordinates that to the <hi>command,</hi> and uſes it onely as a helpe to further his execution of the command. This will the better appeare, if we ſever the dutie from the reward; which meeting together, make it doubtfull (to others at leaſt) which moſt <hi>prevailes</hi> to the motion. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, when <hi>Religion,</hi> and proſperitie, and peace, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite meete together, who, almoſt, is not religious? and it is a hard matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for a by-ſtander, to ſay, which drawes moſt: Sever them and you ſhall ſee ſtraight. Two <hi>Gentlemen</hi> walke together with one man at their heeles: what ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger can ſay, whom he followes? Follow them but till they part, and you ſhall diſcover the man to whom he retaines: So is it here, If to bee religious (in ſuch times, and places, or company may purchaſe a wicked man <hi>danger,</hi> or diſgrace, or ſcorne, &amp;c. you ſhall ſee a hollow heart forſake and almoſt abjure <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſwimme along with the ſtreame: As the <hi>ſtonie-ground-hearers</hi> made faire ſhew till perſecution aroſe,
<note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> and then they were <hi>offended;</hi> which concludes ſtrongly they followed <hi>Religion,</hi> but for <hi>Peace</hi> ſake, and not <hi>Peace</hi> for <hi>Religion.</hi> Now a truly good heart, is <hi>principally</hi> drawne by Gods <hi>Command,</hi> and intire Love to <hi>Religion;</hi> which appeares by this, that ſever Peace from Religion, hee ſtill keepes on his courſe; and though the world frowne or ſcorne, or kill hee will follow his <hi>Religion</hi> ſtill. What uſe then of the <hi>Hope</hi> of reward? why, indeed, if hee may have <hi>Peace</hi> with Religion, hee likes it well, and is ſo much more zealous in his Profeſſion of it; but if not, he cares not for it, but will rather part with <hi>Peace</hi> than with <hi>Religion:</hi> The <hi>hope</hi> of reward is in his eye, but by the by; He takes not up his <hi>Religion</hi> for <hi>Peace,</hi> but makes his advantage of <hi>Peace,</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59698:45"/>to advance his <hi>Religion.</hi> It is a <hi>prettie</hi> phraſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle concerning <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 11.26. not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>he caſt an eye</hi> (after he had made his choice, and was going on his way) <hi>upon the recompence of reward:</hi> Not as a ground of undertaking, but as an <hi>encouragement</hi> of his undertaken journey. As if a father ſhould bid his loving and willing childe goe of ſuch an errand; and when he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily running, ſhould call him backe and ſay; Childe, becauſe I ſee you are ſo willing, to execute my command, looke you, here's <hi>mony</hi> to put in your purſe, to ſpend by the way and here's a <hi>horſe</hi> to carry you with more eaſe; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I will <hi>promiſe</hi> you, you ſhall bee my <hi>heire.</hi> This no doubt, muſt needes put <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>ſpirits</hi> into the Childe, with more cheerefulneſſe to performe his dutie; though he had no eye upon theſe in his firſt ſetting out. In a word, there are two things that further the motion of a clock, the <hi>Plummet,</hi> and the <hi>Oile</hi> beſtowed upon the wheeles; the firſt and chiefeſt is the <hi>Plummet,</hi> that beginnes the motion; the next is the <hi>Oile,</hi> and that facilitates the motion. So, be it a good man hath an <hi>eye</hi> to the reward, yet the <hi>command</hi> of God is the <hi>Plummet,</hi> or prime mover; if he meet with a <hi>Promiſe</hi> by the way, he uſes it as <hi>Oile</hi> to make his motion quicker: The command of God is the principall <hi>Mover,</hi> the hope of reward is but the ſubordinate <hi>helper</hi> of his courſe. And this, I take it, is lawfull, againſt all cavils and excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; A man, firſt looking at God, may in the next place look at himſelfe, and helpe himſelfe, in the ſervice of God, with the hope of a promiſed reward.</p>
                  <p>And this is the thing, I have hitherto intended to urge upon you; The work of <hi>Religion</hi> is not more <hi>laborious,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. The Motive to it.</note> than the Reward promiſed is <hi>glorious:</hi> Looke not ſo much at the <hi>work</hi> as at the <hi>iſſue.</hi> What though you ſee no preſent <hi>profit, Verily there is a reward for the righteous:</hi> Hee that ſowes, ſhall in due ſeaſon reape; Good works are a ſeed, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ſeeme loſt; and we think all is gone. No, they are a <hi>ſeed,</hi> which muſt lye a time under ground, before it can come forth: <hi>He that goeth forth and carries good ſeed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.6.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall come
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59698:46"/>againe with joy, and bring his ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> him.</hi> I uſe but this perſwaſion; The want of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God, is the cauſe of all, or much of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>content</hi> in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, of Magiſtrate, Miniſter, maſter, ſervant, &amp;c. when we find not our labour ſucceſſefull, or that reſpect which we expected upon our conſcionable endevours: <hi>No man, ſo croſſed as I; No man takes ſo much paines to ſo little purpoſe; No man findes ſuch poore reſpects, &amp;c.</hi> It is not becauſe thou <hi>lookeſt</hi> at men, and haſt not an <hi>eye</hi> upon God, and upon the promiſed <hi>Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> of reward? It was a <hi>ſtrong</hi> weakneſſe, and a ſtrange pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimitie for ſuch a Prophet as <hi>Jeremie,</hi> to ſay upon the <hi>non proficiencie</hi> of his people, <hi>I will ſpeake no more in the name of the Lord; Oh that I had a cottage in a garden of Cucumbers,</hi> &amp;c. That was <hi>Heroicall</hi> of another, his fellow, <hi>I have laboured in vaine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 49.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I have ſpent my ſtrength in vaine; yet ſurely my judgement is with the Lord, and my work</hi> (or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) <hi>with my God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2, 3.</note> My brethren (the Lords Miniſters) <hi>bee inſtant, preach the word, in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon;</hi> be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the unprofitableneſſe or unthankfulnes of your people; for you ſerve a good <hi>Maſter,</hi> that will pay you your wages; and the leſſe from them, the <hi>more</hi> you may expect from him: Its that wherewith the Apoſtle encourages ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (of unthankfull and unnaturall maſters) to all ſincere and faithful obedience; <hi>Servants obey your maſters, &amp;c. And whatſoever ye doe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.22, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>doe it heartily, as to the Lord, and not unto men: Knowing that of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye ſhall receive the reward of inheritance; for ye ſerve the Lord Chriſt.</hi> The like I ſay to all eſtates and conditions of men; Whatſoever ye doe, doe it <hi>heartily,</hi> knowing that of the <hi>Lord</hi> ye ſhall receive the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of inheritance. Oh, could we but looke up at <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>promiſe</hi> of Reward, by the <hi>eye</hi> of our <hi>Hope,</hi> how eaſily might wee in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> callings paſſe through good report and ill report, good reſpect and diſ-reſpect, and trample all the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſes</hi> of men under our feet! I conclude all with the words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. laſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Wherefore, my deare brethren, bee ye conſtant, unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know that your labour ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59698:46"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
